<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>DutchNews.nl</title><link>https://www.dutchnews.nl/</link><description>DutchNews.nl brings daily news from The Netherlands in English</description><lastBuildDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 09:13:34 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>Economy minister cancels China mission amid Nexperia tensions</title><link>https://www.dutchnews.nl/2025/12/economy-minister-cancels-china-mission-amid-nexperia-tensions/</link><description><![CDATA[<article class="post-260668 post type-post status-publish format-standard has-post-thumbnail hentry category-business category-china category-chips category-economy category-tech"><header class="pb-4 px-4"><h1 class="text-serif lh-1"> Economy minister cancels China mission amid Nexperia tensions</h1> <time class="text-secondary updated me-2" datetime="2025-12-03T09:12:35+00:00"> December 3, 2025 </time></header><figure aria-describedby="caption-attachment-259956" class="px-lg-5" id="attachment_259956"> <img alt="" class="attachment-full size-full wp-post-image" decoding="async" fetchpriority="high" height="667" sizes="(max-width: 1000px) 100vw, 1000px" src="/wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/vincent-karremans-5.jpg" srcset="/wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/vincent-karremans-5.jpg 1000w, /wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/vincent-karremans-5-560x374.jpg 560w, /wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/vincent-karremans-5-360x240.jpg 360w, /wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/vincent-karremans-5-768x512.jpg 768w" width="1000"/><figcaption class="px-4 px-lg-0" id="caption-attachment-259956"> Economic affairs minister
Vincent Karremans. Photo: Martin Beekman RVD</figcaption></figure><main class="px-4"><p data-end="275" data-start="78">Caretaker economic affairs minister Vincent Karremans has <a href="https://www.tweedekamer.nl/kamerstukken/brieven_regering/detail?id=2025Z21017&amp;did=2025D49646">pulled out</a> of next week’s planned trade mission to China, during which he had also hoped to discuss the ongoing diplomatic row surrounding chipmaker Nexperia.</p><p data-end="611" data-start="277">Karremans was due to depart on December 9 and had planned to meet Chinese counterparts to discuss concerns about the future of the Chinese-Dutch firm, which has its headquarters in Nijmegen.</p><p data-end="611" data-start="277">However, the Chinese ministers he intended to see will be attending the Central Economic Work Conference, making a meeting impossible, he said. Karremans also said a ministerial-level meeting would in any case have been premature because diplomatic talks over Nexperia are still under way.</p><p data-end="611" data-start="277"><div class="ad-container overflow-hidden p-4 bg-light my-8 d-none d-md-block"><div class="bg-light p-lg-2 h-100 w-100 d-flex align-items-center justify-content-center position-relative" data-tagname="ROS_Inarticle"><div id="div-gpt-ad-dutchnews_ros_inarticle" style="display:block;"></div></div></div><div class="ad-container overflow-hidden p-4 bg-light my-8 d-block d-md-none"><div class="bg-light p-lg-2 h-100 w-100 d-flex align-items-center justify-content-center position-relative" data-tagname="ROS_Inarticle"><div id="div-gpt-ad-dutchnews_ros_inarticle-m" style="display:block;"></div></div></div></p><p data-end="1133" data-start="764">The dispute dates back to September, when <a href="https://www.dutchnews.nl/2025/10/minister-to-brief-parliament-on-historic-takeover-at-nexperia/">Karremans placed Nexperia</a> under state supervision amid fears that crucial technological expertise could be shifted out of the Netherlands.</p><p data-end="1133" data-start="764">The government believed the Chinese owner intended to move the company’s intellectual property from Nijmegen to China, which it said would have major consequences for the European economy.</p><p data-end="1307" data-start="1135">Beijing reacted angrily and swiftly imposed an export ban on chips produced by Nexperia in China. The move left carmakers and suppliers uncertain about supplies for weeks.</p><p data-end="1307" data-start="1135"><div class="ad-container overflow-hidden p-4 bg-light my-8 d-none d-md-block"><div class="bg-light p-lg-2 h-100 w-100 d-flex align-items-center justify-content-center position-relative" data-tagname="ROS_Incontent"><div id="div-gpt-ad-dutchnews_ros_incontent" style="display:block;"></div></div></div><div class="ad-container overflow-hidden p-4 bg-light my-8 d-block d-md-none"><div class="bg-light p-lg-2 h-100 w-100 d-flex align-items-center justify-content-center position-relative" data-tagname="ROS_Incontent"><div id="div-gpt-ad-dutchnews_ros_incontent-m" style="display:block;"></div></div></div></p><p data-end="1662" data-start="1309">An official delegation <a href="https://www.dutchnews.nl/2025/11/dutch-delegation-in-china-in-effort-to-end-the-nexperia-dispute/">travelled to China</a> in November to ease tensions, after which Karremans <a href="https://www.dutchnews.nl/2025/11/dutch-pause-intervention-at-nexperia-after-constructive-talks/">suspended the restrictions</a> in an effort to repair relations between the two countries. He later said he no longer saw an immediate risk of Nexperia transferring production to China.</p><p data-end="1994" data-start="1664">Karremans must now explain his handling of the case in parliament, with the debate taking place on Thursday.</p><p data-end="1994" data-start="1664">“If developments around Nexperia give cause to travel to China at short notice, I will do so,” he said, adding that he has agreed on this with China’s minister of commerce.</p><p data-end="2057" data-start="1996">The VNO-NCW-led business delegation will proceed with its visit.</p></main><div class="ad-container overflow-hidden d-none d-md-block p-4 bg-light mt-8 mb-10 mx-lg-4"><div class="bg-light p-lg-2 h-100 w-100 d-flex align-items-center justify-content-center position-relative" data-tagname="ROS_Native"><div id="div-gpt-ad-dutchnews_ros_native" style="display:block;"></div></div></div><div class="ad-container overflow-hidden d-block d-md-none bg-light my-8"><div class="bg-light p-lg-2 h-100 w-100 d-flex align-items-center justify-content-center position-relative" data-tagname="ROS_Native"><div id="div-gpt-ad-dutchnews_ros_native-m" style="display:block;"></div></div></div><footer class="my-8 px-4"><div class="pb-8"></div> <a class="btn btn-secondary btn-sm" href="/category/business/?list"></a> <a class="btn btn-secondary btn-sm" href="/category/china/?list"></a> <a class="btn btn-secondary btn-sm" href="/category/chips/?list"></a> <a class="btn btn-secondary btn-sm" href="/category/economy/?list"></a> <a class="btn btn-secondary btn-sm" href="/category/tech/?list"></a></footer><div class="bg-green-light p-3 mx-4 mt-8 mb-12"></div></article>]]></description><guid>https://www.dutchnews.nl/?p=260668</guid><pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 09:12:35 -0000</pubDate><dc:creator><![CDATA[Robin Pascoe]]></dc:creator></item><item><title>Cnline retailer Bol removes sex dolls from site post court case</title><link>https://www.dutchnews.nl/2025/12/cnline-retailer-bol-removes-sex-dolls-from-site-post-court-case/</link><description><![CDATA[<article class="post-260666 post type-post status-publish format-standard has-post-thumbnail hentry category-abuse category-children category-court-cases category-retail category-sex"><header class="pb-4 px-4"><h1 class="text-serif lh-1"> Cnline retailer Bol removes sex dolls from site post court case</h1> <time class="text-secondary updated me-2" datetime="2025-12-03T08:40:28+00:00"> December 3, 2025 </time></header><figure aria-describedby="caption-attachment-156696" class="px-lg-5" id="attachment_156696"> <img alt="" class="attachment-full size-full wp-post-image" decoding="async" fetchpriority="high" height="667" sizes="(max-width: 1000px) 100vw, 1000px" src="/wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2020/05/bol.com_.jpg" srcset="/wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2020/05/bol.com_.jpg 1000w, /wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2020/05/bol.com_-560x374.jpg 560w, /wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2020/05/bol.com_-360x240.jpg 360w, /wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2020/05/bol.com_-768x512.jpg 768w, /wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2020/05/bol.com_-640x427.jpg 640w, /wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2020/05/bol.com_-92x62.jpg 92w, /wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2020/05/bol.com_-130x87.jpg 130w" width="1000"/><figcaption class="px-4 px-lg-0" id="caption-attachment-156696"> Photo: Depositphotos</figcaption></figure><main class="px-4"><p data-end="80" data-start="0">Oneline retailer Bol has temporarily stopped selling all sex dolls after the conviction of a 38-year-old man for possessing child sex dolls that his lawyers said were purchased through the platform.</p><p data-end="80" data-start="0">According to <a href="https://www.rtl.nl/nieuws/binnenland/artikel/5542029/bol-sekspop-kopen-verboden">RTL Nieuws</a>, sex dolls resembling minors were still available on the site on Tuesday. The dolls were around 1.28 metres tall and of different weights, and the adverts gave graphic details about their physical attributes. Selling or possessing child sex dolls has been illegal in the Netherlands since earlier this year.</p><p data-end="795" data-start="548">In a statement, Bol stressed that offering child sex dolls on its platform is not permitted. The company said it is not liable for products offered by third-party sellers but does take action against partners who violate the law or internal rules.</p><p data-end="795" data-start="548"><div class="ad-container overflow-hidden p-4 bg-light my-8 d-none d-md-block"><div class="bg-light p-lg-2 h-100 w-100 d-flex align-items-center justify-content-center position-relative" data-tagname="ROS_Inarticle"><div id="div-gpt-ad-dutchnews_ros_inarticle" style="display:block;"></div></div></div><div class="ad-container overflow-hidden p-4 bg-light my-8 d-block d-md-none"><div class="bg-light p-lg-2 h-100 w-100 d-flex align-items-center justify-content-center position-relative" data-tagname="ROS_Inarticle"><div id="div-gpt-ad-dutchnews_ros_inarticle-m" style="display:block;"></div></div></div></p><p data-end="1160" data-start="797">“Although we do not know whether the dolls mentioned in the court case were actually purchased via one of our sales partners, the ruling is reason for Bol to take the entire sex-doll category offline for the time being and investigate it thoroughly,” the company said.</p><p data-end="1160" data-start="797">By Tuesday evening the category was still listed on the website, but no products were visible.</p><p data-end="1662" data-start="1393">The man from Hillegom was sentenced last week to three years in prison, one  them suspended. He was convicted of owning two child sex dolls as well as possessing, creating and distributing child pornography. He had also shared a nude photo of his own daughter online.</p><p data-end="2130" data-start="1896">Chinese retailer Shein faced similar criticism last month after French authorities threatened to block the site over the sale of child sex dolls. Shein removed the dolls, as well as weapons, and was allowed to remain online in France.</p></main><div class="ad-container overflow-hidden d-none d-md-block p-4 bg-light mt-8 mb-10 mx-lg-4"><div class="bg-light p-lg-2 h-100 w-100 d-flex align-items-center justify-content-center position-relative" data-tagname="ROS_Native"><div id="div-gpt-ad-dutchnews_ros_native" style="display:block;"></div></div></div><div class="ad-container overflow-hidden d-block d-md-none bg-light my-8"><div class="bg-light p-lg-2 h-100 w-100 d-flex align-items-center justify-content-center position-relative" data-tagname="ROS_Native"><div id="div-gpt-ad-dutchnews_ros_native-m" style="display:block;"></div></div></div><footer class="my-8 px-4"><div class="pb-8"></div> <a class="btn btn-secondary btn-sm" href="/category/abuse/?list"></a> <a class="btn btn-secondary btn-sm" href="/category/children/?list"></a> <a class="btn btn-secondary btn-sm" href="/category/court-cases/?list"></a> <a class="btn btn-secondary btn-sm" href="/category/retail/?list"></a> <a class="btn btn-secondary btn-sm" href="/category/sex/?list"></a></footer><div class="bg-green-light p-3 mx-4 mt-8 mb-12"></div></article>]]></description><guid>https://www.dutchnews.nl/?p=260666</guid><pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 08:40:28 -0000</pubDate><dc:creator><![CDATA[Robin Pascoe]]></dc:creator></item><item><title>“Selling a house in NL is like living in two parallel worlds”</title><link>https://www.dutchnews.nl/2025/12/selling-a-house-in-nl-is-like-living-in-two-parallel-worlds/</link><description><![CDATA[<article class="post-259946 post type-post status-publish format-standard has-post-thumbnail hentry category-housing type-column"><header class="pb-4 px-4"><h1 class="text-serif lh-1"> “Selling a house in NL is like living in two parallel worlds”</h1> <time class="text-secondary updated me-2" datetime="2025-12-03T08:13:23+00:00"> December 3, 2025 </time></header><figure aria-describedby="caption-attachment-260148" class="px-lg-5" id="attachment_260148"> <img alt="" class="attachment-full size-full wp-post-image" decoding="async" fetchpriority="high" height="1512" sizes="(max-width: 2016px) 100vw, 2016px" src="/wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/IMG_0711.jpg" srcset="/wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/IMG_0711.jpg 2016w, /wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/IMG_0711-560x420.jpg 560w, /wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/IMG_0711-1200x900.jpg 1200w, /wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/IMG_0711-768x576.jpg 768w, /wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/IMG_0711-1536x1152.jpg 1536w" width="2016"/><figcaption class="px-4 px-lg-0" id="caption-attachment-260148"> Photo: Dutch News</figcaption></figure><main class="px-4"><p><strong>Buying and selling property in the Netherlands is not good for your blood pressure, says </strong><strong>Steve White, after experiencing what it is really like to deal with estate agents, hidden fees and obsessions with being tidy.</strong></p><p>My Dutch wife and I have recently forced ourselves through the property mangle by uprooting ourselves from the unstylish but modernist newtown of child-friendly Almere, to the ritzy international-lawyer-strewn boulevards of the nation’s political capital – The Hague.</p><p>When we sold our two bedroomed flat in unfashionable north London 25 years ago, before moving to Almere, the property market was not as brutish as it is now.</p><p>Our UK sale went ahead after a minimal amount of desultory Marrakech-market-type haggling, and we accepted an offer that was marginally less than the asking price. In today’s meaty Dutch market offering less than the asking price in property hot spots (propspots ) like Utrecht, Amsterdam, Rotterdam or The Hague, will have disbelieving sellers and their agents slapping their thighs in mirth whilst showing you the door.</p><p>“It’s a horrible system, this secret bidding thing. Why not just have an open, online auction? You bid up to your budget, and if it goes higher, that’s tough,” we ask. “This is the way we do it here,” we are told.</p><div class="ad-container overflow-hidden p-4 bg-light my-8 d-none d-md-block"><div class="bg-light p-lg-2 h-100 w-100 d-flex align-items-center justify-content-center position-relative" data-tagname="ROS_Inarticle"><div id="div-gpt-ad-dutchnews_ros_inarticle" style="display:block;"></div></div></div><div class="ad-container overflow-hidden p-4 bg-light my-8 d-block d-md-none"><div class="bg-light p-lg-2 h-100 w-100 d-flex align-items-center justify-content-center position-relative" data-tagname="ROS_Inarticle"><div id="div-gpt-ad-dutchnews_ros_inarticle-m" style="display:block;"></div></div></div><p>We bid on one apartment and later found out that our offer was third highest. The second highest bid was €1,000 more than ours. The ‘winning’ bid was €26,000 more. In theory, in an open auction, that buyer could have bid €1 more than the next highest bid and they would have had €25,999 in the bank for a new kitchen, which the place sorely needed.</p><p>When we started looking for apartments we were advised that we could never hope to buy a place in a propspot without hiring an <em>aankoopmakelaar</em>.  They are hotshot agents of the property world. They will do all the donkey work regarding your move – check locations, accompany you on inspection tours, liaise with selling agents, check contracts, advise on the financials etc etc.</p><p>An <em>aankoopmakelaar</em> may suggest that you don’t bid an exact amount, on a property, say €500,000, but, €500,579. This random amount would just top a typical round figure bid. Why would a seller eschew an extra €579? That’s half a decent tumble dryer for their new place.</p><p>We saw this phenomenon many times and employed it ourselves with spectacular results. On the apartment we eventually purchased our extraneous amount of a few hundred euros actually related to the months of our daughters’ birthdays. The next highest bid, also with an obscure figure tagged on, was just €134 lower. I fear their kids were born in the wrong months.</p><div class="ad-container overflow-hidden p-4 bg-light my-8 d-none d-md-block"><div class="bg-light p-lg-2 h-100 w-100 d-flex align-items-center justify-content-center position-relative" data-tagname="ROS_Incontent"><div id="div-gpt-ad-dutchnews_ros_incontent" style="display:block;"></div></div></div><div class="ad-container overflow-hidden p-4 bg-light my-8 d-block d-md-none"><div class="bg-light p-lg-2 h-100 w-100 d-flex align-items-center justify-content-center position-relative" data-tagname="ROS_Incontent"><div id="div-gpt-ad-dutchnews_ros_incontent-m" style="display:block;"></div></div></div><p>As with any group of like minded professionals a quasi masonic <em>aankoopmakelaar</em> sub-culture exists in which the industry specialists trade rumours, gossip, chitchat, nudges, winks and inside information – all potentially indispensable knowledge that mere buyers could never be privvy to.</p><p>The bidding process itself is opaque, deadlines are there to be broken, nothing in the process is written in stone, let alone bricks, or indeed mortar. Money talks louder than deadlines. So, how much to overbid exactly?</p><p>At the time of writing, in three of the propspots, I would  say this: Utrecht, 15-20%; The Hague, 10-15%; Almere, 7-10%. But the market changes quickly. I am not an <em>aankoopmakelaar</em>. You have not paid me three grand upfront (€3000). Please don’t quote me on this.</p><h2>Celebrating</h2><p>While we were smugly celebrating our unaided success we alas failed to hear an overexcited cash register clanging away in the background, a sound which accompanies every house sale – financial advisor (€3000); notaries (€2000); transfer tax (2% of the selling price; 0% on newbuilds); Taxatie report (€150-€775); and, for the linguistically challenged, translators (€250).</p><p>The euphoria of having eventually secured a place quickly dissipated when we realised we had to sell our own house, something that had, up to this point, apparently not crossed our minds.</p><p>And when you are selling a house in the Netherlands you suddenly start living in two parallel worlds: the world of your normal, messy life, juxtaposed alongside the wonderful white and empty world of Makelaarlaland.</p><p>Dutch <em>makelaars</em> (fee: 1-1.5% of the sale price) will suggest your chances of a sale improve if your house is white and empty. Unless you happen to live in a disused salt mine you are thus required to paint all the walls white and despatch all your personal belongings to the local dump.</p><h2>Quick paint job</h2><p>So we had to shape up. Apart from doing a rapid paint job and securing the mandatory energy rating (€280), we quickly learned that in Makelaarlaland these things are unwelcome: all personal items (especially family photos); unsightly kitchen equipment; old style pedestal toilets; untidy books; too much furniture;  loose wires; cats; dead plants; colour; junk; mess.</p><p>When the makelaar came to inspect our house before the first viewings it echoed like a coroner’s corridor. We had thrown out enough noise-swallowing fabrics and furnishings to kit out a childs’ soft play area. Our house was no longer a house, but a commodity to sell.</p><p>We achieved our Makelaarlaland state of nirvana by ruthlessly editing our junk. We spent so much time at the local recycling centre we were given a loyalty card. And once we had de-cluttered, and tidied the place up it was time for our makelaar’s photographer (€650-€750) to take photographs using his Naomi-Campbell-Tardis Lens, a unique optical attachment which makes all houses look way more beautiful, and far bigger on the inside, than they actually are.</p><h2>Viewing days</h2><p>These photographs ended up on funda.nl, the pre-eminent Dutch website in the Netherlands for buying/selling/renting houses/apartments. And, of course, everything must remain tidy for at least  3-4 viewing days. In Makelaarlaland this means you are forever frantically secreting unsightly household objects, usually in places they don’t belong.</p><p>“Where are the toothbrush chargers?” I asked my wife. “Try the cupboard under the stairs,” she replied.</p><p>The problem with giving your house the mother of all spring cleans is that it suddenly becomes a decent place to live. I quite liked our house now. Do I really want to move?</p><h2>More costs</h2><p>But we had to. After all, we had a buyer and had booked  a removal company (€1500-€3500, depending on distance, location, how much packing you want to do yourself etc).</p><p>So did my stress levels soar during this whole process? Absolutely. Especially during the bidding process for the houses we bought and sold. And I almost suffered a nervous breakdown when I quietly pondered that we were spending quite a few hundred thousand euros on a property that we had only seen twice, for 20 minutes each time.</p><p>To save you all locating the calculator app on your phone, and using an extremely broad emulsion brush, when you buy and sell a house in the region of €500,000 expect to pay anything between €25,000-€30,000 on all the extraneous expenses. Plus €579, of course.</p></main><div class="ad-container overflow-hidden d-none d-md-block p-4 bg-light mt-8 mb-10 mx-lg-4"><div class="bg-light p-lg-2 h-100 w-100 d-flex align-items-center justify-content-center position-relative" data-tagname="ROS_Native"><div id="div-gpt-ad-dutchnews_ros_native" style="display:block;"></div></div></div><div class="ad-container overflow-hidden d-block d-md-none bg-light my-8"><div class="bg-light p-lg-2 h-100 w-100 d-flex align-items-center justify-content-center position-relative" data-tagname="ROS_Native"><div id="div-gpt-ad-dutchnews_ros_native-m" style="display:block;"></div></div></div><footer class="my-8 px-4"><div class="pb-8"></div> <a class="btn btn-primary btn-sm" href="/life-in-the-netherlands/column/"></a> <a class="btn btn-secondary btn-sm" href="/category/housing/?list"></a></footer><div class="bg-green-light p-3 mx-4 mt-8 mb-12"></div></article>]]></description><guid>https://www.dutchnews.nl/?p=259946</guid><pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 08:13:23 -0000</pubDate><dc:creator><![CDATA[Robin Pascoe]]></dc:creator></item><item><title>D66 and CDA aim to woo coalition partners with “open invitation”</title><link>https://www.dutchnews.nl/2025/12/d66-and-cda-aim-to-woo-coalition-partners-with-open-invitation/</link><description><![CDATA[<article class="post-260656 post type-post status-publish format-standard has-post-thumbnail hentry category-election-2025 category-politics"><header class="pb-4 px-4"><h1 class="text-serif lh-1"> D66 and CDA aim to woo coalition partners with “open invitation”</h1> <time class="text-secondary updated me-2" datetime="2025-12-02T17:04:18+00:00"> December 2, 2025 </time></header><figure aria-describedby="caption-attachment-260657" class="px-lg-5" id="attachment_260657"> <img alt="" class="attachment-full size-full wp-post-image" decoding="async" fetchpriority="high" height="1987" sizes="(max-width: 2560px) 100vw, 2560px" src="/wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2025/12/ANP-543681437-scaled.jpg" srcset="/wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2025/12/ANP-543681437-scaled.jpg 2560w, /wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2025/12/ANP-543681437-560x435.jpg 560w, /wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2025/12/ANP-543681437-1200x932.jpg 1200w, /wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2025/12/ANP-543681437-768x596.jpg 768w, /wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2025/12/ANP-543681437-1536x1192.jpg 1536w, /wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2025/12/ANP-543681437-2048x1590.jpg 2048w" width="2560"/><figcaption class="px-4 px-lg-0" id="caption-attachment-260657"> Henri Bontenbal (l) of the CDA and D66 leader Rob Jetten at the presentation of the policy document. Photo: ANP/Sem van der Wal</figcaption></figure><main class="px-4"><p>The two parties working to form a new Dutch government, D66 and CDA, have produced a joint policy document that they hope will form the basis of a coalition agreement.</p><p>Sybrand Buma, the former CDA party leader chairing the negotiations, said he would talk to all parties in parliament over the next week to gauge support the two parties’ ideas, either as coalition partners or through confidence and supply agreements.</p><p>The progressive-liberal D66 and the Christian Democrats have spent the last two weeks brainstorming five key policy areas: housing, migration, the economy, nitrogen reduction and defence.</p><div class="ad-container overflow-hidden p-4 bg-light my-8 d-none d-md-block"><div class="bg-light p-lg-2 h-100 w-100 d-flex align-items-center justify-content-center position-relative" data-tagname="ROS_Inarticle"><div id="div-gpt-ad-dutchnews_ros_inarticle" style="display:block;"></div></div></div><div class="ad-container overflow-hidden p-4 bg-light my-8 d-block d-md-none"><div class="bg-light p-lg-2 h-100 w-100 d-flex align-items-center justify-content-center position-relative" data-tagname="ROS_Inarticle"><div id="div-gpt-ad-dutchnews_ros_inarticle-m" style="display:block;"></div></div></div><p>The parties want to retain the contentious “spreading law” that requires all councils to house a proportionate share of refugees but also introduce stricter asylum rules and a three-year residency permit for some categories of refugees.</p><p>They also set out plans to phase out mortgage income tax relief for homeowners – an idea strongly opposed by the right-wing parties VVD and JA21 – and build 21 large-scale housing projects across the country.</p><p>The document also states the “expat ruling will be restored” – possibly referring to a planned cut in the tax break in 2027 – and the nationality act will be modernised so that “Dutch nationals living abroad will not lose their nationality more quickly than those in Germany, France, Belgium and Britain”.</p><h2>“Ambitious agenda”</h2><p>The two leaders, Rob Jetten of D66 and Henri Bontenbal of CDA, stressed that they had left plenty of scope for other parties to include their own ideas, particularly on how to finance their “positive and ambitious agenda”.</p><p>Jetten said the 17-page document was “not a detailed coalition agreement but an outstretched hand”, while Bontenbal called it an “open invitation to hold talks with other parties”.</p><p>Both leaders talked up the constructive and harmonious nature of their discussions in the last two weeks and pointedly contrasted it with the fractious relations between the partners in the last right-wing coalition.</p><div class="ad-container overflow-hidden p-4 bg-light my-8 d-none d-md-block"><div class="bg-light p-lg-2 h-100 w-100 d-flex align-items-center justify-content-center position-relative" data-tagname="ROS_Incontent"><div id="div-gpt-ad-dutchnews_ros_incontent" style="display:block;"></div></div></div><div class="ad-container overflow-hidden p-4 bg-light my-8 d-block d-md-none"><div class="bg-light p-lg-2 h-100 w-100 d-flex align-items-center justify-content-center position-relative" data-tagname="ROS_Incontent"><div id="div-gpt-ad-dutchnews_ros_incontent-m" style="display:block;"></div></div></div><p>“A lot of people in this country have seen politicians in recent years do nothing but put off solutions when we so badly need to see progress and results,” Jetten said.</p><p>Bontenbal said he and Jetten shared “a wish to do politics differently: constructively, respectfully and with a focus on substance”.</p><p>“We are building bridges to haul ourselves out of the trenches and help the Netherlands move forward,” he said.</p><h2>Open mind</h2><p>Buma said some topics had deliberately been left out of the interim report, such as justice, education and government reforms, to give other parties the chance to put their own stamp on a future coalition agreement.</p><p>“I hope that other parties will look at this agenda with an open mind,” Buma said.  “It should be read as an invitation that hopefully other political parties, but also organisations in society, social partners and other branches of government can find opportunities to co-operate.”</p><p>He said he would consult other parties over the next week before submitting his final report to parliament on December 9.</p><h2>Majority cabinet</h2><p data-end="1010" data-is-last-node="" data-is-only-node="" data-start="869">At least two more parties will be needed to have a majority in the lower house of parliament and the right-wing VVD and GroenLinks-PvdA alliance are the most likely candidates. But the VVD has so far refused to work together with the left-wing parties.</p><p>VVD leader Dilan Yesilgöz reiterated her support for a centre-right government in her <a href="https://x.com/DilanYesilgoz/status/1995892109656637471">social media reaction</a> to the interim report. “We are ready to talk,” she said, “and to take the next steps towards a centre-right alliance and thereby do justice to the wishes of voters.”</p><p>Jesse Klaver, leader of the left-wing grouping GroenLinks-PvdA, said he welcomed the D66 and CDA efforts to build bridges between the parites. Their plan, he said, “is not social or green enough but we see enough reason for detailed negotiations to form a majority cabinet.”</p></main><div class="ad-container overflow-hidden d-none d-md-block p-4 bg-light mt-8 mb-10 mx-lg-4"><div class="bg-light p-lg-2 h-100 w-100 d-flex align-items-center justify-content-center position-relative" data-tagname="ROS_Native"><div id="div-gpt-ad-dutchnews_ros_native" style="display:block;"></div></div></div><div class="ad-container overflow-hidden d-block d-md-none bg-light my-8"><div class="bg-light p-lg-2 h-100 w-100 d-flex align-items-center justify-content-center position-relative" data-tagname="ROS_Native"><div id="div-gpt-ad-dutchnews_ros_native-m" style="display:block;"></div></div></div><footer class="my-8 px-4"><div class="pb-8"></div> <a class="btn btn-secondary btn-sm" href="/category/election-2025/?list"></a> <a class="btn btn-secondary btn-sm" href="/category/politics/?list"></a></footer><div class="bg-green-light p-3 mx-4 mt-8 mb-12"></div></article>]]></description><guid>https://www.dutchnews.nl/?p=260656</guid><pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 17:04:18 -0000</pubDate><dc:creator><![CDATA[Gordon Darroch]]></dc:creator></item><item><title>D66 and CDA agree contours of new Dutch coalition deal</title><link>https://www.dutchnews.nl/2025/12/d66-and-cda-agree-contours-of-dutch-coalition-deal/</link><description><![CDATA[<article class="post-260650 post type-post status-publish format-standard has-post-thumbnail hentry category-cda category-d66 category-election-2025 category-politics newsletter-top-article"><header class="pb-4 px-4"><h1 class="text-serif lh-1"> D66 and CDA agree contours of new Dutch coalition deal</h1> <time class="text-secondary updated me-2" datetime="2025-12-02T15:12:49+00:00"> December 2, 2025 </time></header><figure aria-describedby="caption-attachment-260652" class="px-lg-5" id="attachment_260652"> <img alt="" class="attachment-full size-full wp-post-image" decoding="async" fetchpriority="high" height="786" sizes="(max-width: 1000px) 100vw, 1000px" src="/wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2025/12/ANP-543669595.jpg" srcset="/wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2025/12/ANP-543669595.jpg 1000w, /wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2025/12/ANP-543669595-560x440.jpg 560w, /wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2025/12/ANP-543669595-768x604.jpg 768w" width="1000"/><figcaption class="px-4 px-lg-0" id="caption-attachment-260652"> Rob Jetten (left) and Henri Bontenbal (right) leaving their talks. Photo: Sem van de Wal ANP</figcaption></figure><main class="px-4"><p data-end="193" data-start="0">The two parties currently in talks on forming a new coalition government for the Netherlands have reached agreement on a number of major issues that will shape the contours of the next cabinet.</p><p data-end="448" data-start="195">Rob Jetten, leader of the liberal democratic party D66, and Christian Democrat leader Henri Bontenbal have been in discussions for just over two weeks under the leadership of Sybrand Buma, who is due to make a statement on the progress later on Tuesday.</p><p data-end="716" data-start="450">“I think we will be able to surprise you with some of the choices,” Jetten told reporters ahead of the final meeting with Buma. The agreement, he said, forms “a good basis for the continuation of the cabinet formation process”.</p><p data-end="716" data-start="450"><div class="ad-container overflow-hidden p-4 bg-light my-8 d-none d-md-block"><div class="bg-light p-lg-2 h-100 w-100 d-flex align-items-center justify-content-center position-relative" data-tagname="ROS_Inarticle"><div id="div-gpt-ad-dutchnews_ros_inarticle" style="display:block;"></div></div></div><div class="ad-container overflow-hidden p-4 bg-light my-8 d-block d-md-none"><div class="bg-light p-lg-2 h-100 w-100 d-flex align-items-center justify-content-center position-relative" data-tagname="ROS_Inarticle"><div id="div-gpt-ad-dutchnews_ros_inarticle-m" style="display:block;"></div></div></div></p><p data-end="867" data-start="718">The main themes outlined by Jetten and Bontenbal before the talks began were housing, the nitrogen crisis, migration, the economy and foreign policy.</p><p data-end="1010" data-is-last-node="" data-is-only-node="" data-start="869">The interim report will now form the basis of talks with other parties, with the aim of putting together a stable government of four parties.</p><p data-end="1010" data-is-last-node="" data-is-only-node="" data-start="869">At least two more parties will be needed to have a majority in the lower house of parliament and the right-wing VVD and GroenLinks-PvdA alliance are the most likely candidates. But the VVD has so far refused to work together with the left-wing parties.</p><p data-end="1010" data-is-last-node="" data-is-only-node="" data-start="869"><em>More to follow</em></p></main><div class="ad-container overflow-hidden d-none d-md-block p-4 bg-light mt-8 mb-10 mx-lg-4"><div class="bg-light p-lg-2 h-100 w-100 d-flex align-items-center justify-content-center position-relative" data-tagname="ROS_Native"><div id="div-gpt-ad-dutchnews_ros_native" style="display:block;"></div></div></div><div class="ad-container overflow-hidden d-block d-md-none bg-light my-8"><div class="bg-light p-lg-2 h-100 w-100 d-flex align-items-center justify-content-center position-relative" data-tagname="ROS_Native"><div id="div-gpt-ad-dutchnews_ros_native-m" style="display:block;"></div></div></div><footer class="my-8 px-4"><div class="pb-8"></div> <a class="btn btn-secondary btn-sm" href="/category/cda/?list"></a> <a class="btn btn-secondary btn-sm" href="/category/d66/?list"></a> <a class="btn btn-secondary btn-sm" href="/category/election-2025/?list"></a> <a class="btn btn-secondary btn-sm" href="/category/politics/?list"></a></footer><div class="bg-green-light p-3 mx-4 mt-8 mb-12"></div></article>]]></description><guid>https://www.dutchnews.nl/?p=260650</guid><pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 15:12:49 -0000</pubDate><dc:creator><![CDATA[Robin Pascoe]]></dc:creator></item><item><title>Just Eat Takeaway founder Jitse Groen steps down after 25 years</title><link>https://www.dutchnews.nl/2025/12/just-eat-takeaway-founder-jitse-groen-steps-down-after-25-years/</link><description><![CDATA[<article class="post-260648 post type-post status-publish format-standard has-post-thumbnail hentry category-business"><header class="pb-4 px-4"><h1 class="text-serif lh-1"> Just Eat Takeaway founder Jitse Groen steps down after 25 years</h1> <time class="text-secondary updated me-2" datetime="2025-12-02T13:44:01+00:00"> December 2, 2025 </time></header><figure aria-describedby="caption-attachment-186751" class="px-lg-5" id="attachment_186751"> <img alt="" class="attachment-full size-full wp-post-image" decoding="async" fetchpriority="high" height="667" sizes="(max-width: 1000px) 100vw, 1000px" src="/wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/Depositphotos_440075520_S.jpg" srcset="/wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/Depositphotos_440075520_S.jpg 1000w, /wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/Depositphotos_440075520_S-560x374.jpg 560w, /wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/Depositphotos_440075520_S-360x240.jpg 360w, /wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/Depositphotos_440075520_S-768x512.jpg 768w, /wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/Depositphotos_440075520_S-640x427.jpg 640w, /wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/Depositphotos_440075520_S-92x62.jpg 92w, /wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/Depositphotos_440075520_S-130x87.jpg 130w" width="1000"/><figcaption class="px-4 px-lg-0" id="caption-attachment-186751"> Food delivery riders in Amsterdam. Photo: Depositphotos.com</figcaption></figure><main class="px-4"><p data-end="374" data-start="71">Jitse Groen will step down as chief executive of Just Eat Takeaway on January 1, 2026, ending a 25-year tenure at the company he founded.</p><p data-end="374" data-start="71">The meal delivery firm announced on Tuesday that he will be succeeded by Roberto Gandolfo, currently chair of Just Eat’s supervisory board and head of Prosus Europe.</p><p data-end="706" data-start="376">The leadership change follows Prosus’s <a href="https://www.dutchnews.nl/2025/02/prosus-bids-e4-1-billion-for-delivery-group-just-eat-takeaway/">€4.1 billion takeover</a> of Just Eat Takeaway earlier this year, which resulted in the company delisting from the Amsterdam stock exchange.</p><p data-end="706" data-start="376"><div class="ad-container overflow-hidden p-4 bg-light my-8 d-none d-md-block"><div class="bg-light p-lg-2 h-100 w-100 d-flex align-items-center justify-content-center position-relative" data-tagname="ROS_Inarticle"><div id="div-gpt-ad-dutchnews_ros_inarticle" style="display:block;"></div></div></div><div class="ad-container overflow-hidden p-4 bg-light my-8 d-block d-md-none"><div class="bg-light p-lg-2 h-100 w-100 d-flex align-items-center justify-content-center position-relative" data-tagname="ROS_Inarticle"><div id="div-gpt-ad-dutchnews_ros_inarticle-m" style="display:block;"></div></div></div></p><p data-end="986" data-start="708">Prosus had initially said in October, shortly after the takeover closed, that Groen and the rest of the management team would stay on. Gandolfo only became head of Prosus Europe this year, having spent a decade at Brazilian delivery service iFood, which is also owned by Prosus.</p><p data-end="1662" data-start="1389">Groen founded Just Eat 25 years ago from his student room in Enschede. The firm initially operated as Thuisbezorgd.nl, which remains the Dutch arm of Just Eat and  now serves around 60 million customers globally, who placed some €19 billion worth of orders in 2024.</p><p data-end="1967" data-start="1664">In a brief statement, Groen described his time at the company as a “special journey” and said he was “incredibly proud” of what the team has built.</p><p data-end="1967" data-start="1664"><div class="ad-container overflow-hidden p-4 bg-light my-8 d-none d-md-block"><div class="bg-light p-lg-2 h-100 w-100 d-flex align-items-center justify-content-center position-relative" data-tagname="ROS_Incontent"><div id="div-gpt-ad-dutchnews_ros_incontent" style="display:block;"></div></div></div><div class="ad-container overflow-hidden p-4 bg-light my-8 d-block d-md-none"><div class="bg-light p-lg-2 h-100 w-100 d-flex align-items-center justify-content-center position-relative" data-tagname="ROS_Incontent"><div id="div-gpt-ad-dutchnews_ros_incontent-m" style="display:block;"></div></div></div></p><p data-end="1967" data-start="1664">In a video message to staff seen by the Financieele Dagblad, he acknowledged that the announcement “will come as a shock to many” and said that “change is never easy”.</p><p>In 2019, Takeaway was demoted to Amsterdam’s Midkap index and its place was taken by then arch rival Prosus. At the time, the two companies were embroiled in a takeover battle for British delivery firm Just Eat, which Takeaway won.</p><p>Prosus, a technology stock and part of South African group Naspers, listed in Amsterdam in September 2019.</p></main><div class="ad-container overflow-hidden d-none d-md-block p-4 bg-light mt-8 mb-10 mx-lg-4"><div class="bg-light p-lg-2 h-100 w-100 d-flex align-items-center justify-content-center position-relative" data-tagname="ROS_Native"><div id="div-gpt-ad-dutchnews_ros_native" style="display:block;"></div></div></div><div class="ad-container overflow-hidden d-block d-md-none bg-light my-8"><div class="bg-light p-lg-2 h-100 w-100 d-flex align-items-center justify-content-center position-relative" data-tagname="ROS_Native"><div id="div-gpt-ad-dutchnews_ros_native-m" style="display:block;"></div></div></div><footer class="my-8 px-4"><div class="pb-8"></div> <a class="btn btn-secondary btn-sm" href="/category/business/?list"></a></footer><div class="bg-green-light p-3 mx-4 mt-8 mb-12"></div></article>]]></description><guid>https://www.dutchnews.nl/?p=260648</guid><pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 13:44:01 -0000</pubDate><dc:creator><![CDATA[Robin Pascoe]]></dc:creator></item><item><title>Gelderland extends its licence to shoot its “problem wolf”</title><link>https://www.dutchnews.nl/2025/12/gelderland-extends-its-licence-to-shoot-its-problem-wolf/</link><description><![CDATA[<article class="post-260645 post type-post status-publish format-standard has-post-thumbnail hentry category-animal-welfare category-court-cases category-gelderland category-wolf"><header class="pb-4 px-4"><h1 class="text-serif lh-1"> Gelderland extends its licence to shoot its “problem wolf”</h1> <time class="text-secondary updated me-2" datetime="2025-12-02T13:36:16+00:00"> December 2, 2025 </time></header><figure aria-describedby="caption-attachment-251633" class="px-lg-5" id="attachment_251633"> <img alt="" class="attachment-full size-full wp-post-image" decoding="async" fetchpriority="high" height="735" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" src="/wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2025/05/Howling_wolf.jpg" srcset="/wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2025/05/Howling_wolf.jpg 1024w, /wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2025/05/Howling_wolf-560x402.jpg 560w, /wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2025/05/Howling_wolf-768x551.jpg 768w" width="1024"/><figcaption class="px-4 px-lg-0" id="caption-attachment-251633"> Photo: Fool4myCanon via Wikimedia Commons</figcaption></figure><main class="px-4"><p data-end="350" data-start="76">The province of Gelderland has extended and widened the licence to shoot a wolf that bit a jogger in the Hoge Veluwe heathland region earlier this year, news website Nu.nl reported on Tuesday.</p><p>The young wolf, known as GW4655m, may now be targeted in a larger area of the countryside, including the grounds of the Deelen airbase, officials said.</p><p data-end="528" data-start="352">Gelderland had issued a licence valid to shoot the wolf until the end of this year but the animal has not been seen for some time. However, members of its pack were recently spotted again near the airbase prompting the province to extend the hunting area.</p><p data-end="528" data-start="352"><div class="ad-container overflow-hidden p-4 bg-light my-8 d-none d-md-block"><div class="bg-light p-lg-2 h-100 w-100 d-flex align-items-center justify-content-center position-relative" data-tagname="ROS_Inarticle"><div id="div-gpt-ad-dutchnews_ros_inarticle" style="display:block;"></div></div></div><div class="ad-container overflow-hidden p-4 bg-light my-8 d-block d-md-none"><div class="bg-light p-lg-2 h-100 w-100 d-flex align-items-center justify-content-center position-relative" data-tagname="ROS_Inarticle"><div id="div-gpt-ad-dutchnews_ros_inarticle-m" style="display:block;"></div></div></div></p><p>The authorisation now runs until July 1, 2026. Gelderland said it opted for a limited extension because killing a wolf is a “serious step”.</p><p data-end="1348" data-start="1127">Campaign group Animal Rights said it will challenge the extension in court. The organisation argues there have been no recent incidents and says the existing permit has proved ineffective because the province has not managed to find the animal.</p><p data-end="1555" data-start="1350">Animal welfare groups recently won a separate case involving another Gelderland wolf linked to 20 attacks on sheep. The court ruled the province must first investigate alternatives for protecting the animals before considering lethal measures.</p></main><div class="ad-container overflow-hidden d-none d-md-block p-4 bg-light mt-8 mb-10 mx-lg-4"><div class="bg-light p-lg-2 h-100 w-100 d-flex align-items-center justify-content-center position-relative" data-tagname="ROS_Native"><div id="div-gpt-ad-dutchnews_ros_native" style="display:block;"></div></div></div><div class="ad-container overflow-hidden d-block d-md-none bg-light my-8"><div class="bg-light p-lg-2 h-100 w-100 d-flex align-items-center justify-content-center position-relative" data-tagname="ROS_Native"><div id="div-gpt-ad-dutchnews_ros_native-m" style="display:block;"></div></div></div><footer class="my-8 px-4"><div class="pb-8"></div> <a class="btn btn-secondary btn-sm" href="/category/animal-welfare/?list"></a> <a class="btn btn-secondary btn-sm" href="/category/court-cases/?list"></a> <a class="btn btn-secondary btn-sm" href="/category/gelderland/?list"></a> <a class="btn btn-secondary btn-sm" href="/category/wolf/?list"></a></footer><div class="bg-green-light p-3 mx-4 mt-8 mb-12"></div></article>]]></description><guid>https://www.dutchnews.nl/?p=260645</guid><pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 13:36:16 -0000</pubDate><dc:creator><![CDATA[Robin Pascoe]]></dc:creator></item><item><title>Elections can be held sooner if government takes action</title><link>https://www.dutchnews.nl/2025/12/elections-can-be-held-sooner-if-government-takes-action/</link><description><![CDATA[<article class="post-260643 post type-post status-publish format-standard has-post-thumbnail hentry category-election category-politics"><header class="pb-4 px-4"><h1 class="text-serif lh-1"> Elections can be held sooner if government takes action</h1> <time class="text-secondary updated me-2" datetime="2025-12-02T11:47:43+00:00"> December 2, 2025 </time></header><figure aria-describedby="caption-attachment-227825" class="px-lg-5" id="attachment_227825"> <img alt="" class="attachment-full size-full wp-post-image" decoding="async" fetchpriority="high" height="1920" sizes="(max-width: 2560px) 100vw, 2560px" src="/wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2023/12/GD-thanks-for-voting-poster-scaled.jpg" srcset="/wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2023/12/GD-thanks-for-voting-poster-scaled.jpg 2560w, /wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2023/12/GD-thanks-for-voting-poster-560x420.jpg 560w, /wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2023/12/GD-thanks-for-voting-poster-1200x900.jpg 1200w, /wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2023/12/GD-thanks-for-voting-poster-768x576.jpg 768w, /wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2023/12/GD-thanks-for-voting-poster-1536x1152.jpg 1536w, /wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2023/12/GD-thanks-for-voting-poster-2048x1536.jpg 2048w" width="2560"/><figcaption class="px-4 px-lg-0" id="caption-attachment-227825"> Photo: Dutch News</figcaption></figure><main class="px-4"><p>Elections could be held within three months of a cabinet collapsing, but only if the government is prepared to invest more in the preparations, the electoral council has said.</p><p>The body responsible for running elections <a href="https://www.kiesraad.nl/adviezen-en-publicaties/adviezen/2025/12/01/advies-sneller-naar-de-stembus-bij-tussentijdse-verkiezingen">produced a report</a> responding to criticism from MPs that the process took too long.</p><p>The current cabinet, led by Dick Schoof, fell on June 3 when Geert Wilders withdrew the far-right PVV from the coalition, but the election took place almost five months later on October 29.</p><div class="ad-container overflow-hidden p-4 bg-light my-8 d-none d-md-block"><div class="bg-light p-lg-2 h-100 w-100 d-flex align-items-center justify-content-center position-relative" data-tagname="ROS_Inarticle"><div id="div-gpt-ad-dutchnews_ros_inarticle" style="display:block;"></div></div></div><div class="ad-container overflow-hidden p-4 bg-light my-8 d-block d-md-none"><div class="bg-light p-lg-2 h-100 w-100 d-flex align-items-center justify-content-center position-relative" data-tagname="ROS_Inarticle"><div id="div-gpt-ad-dutchnews_ros_inarticle-m" style="display:block;"></div></div></div><p>The electoral council (<em>kiesraad</em>) said the process could be speeded up, but chairman Wim Kuijen said it required the government to make “fundamental choices”.</p><p>That included ensuring enough council staff are available during holiday periods to manage the process and keeping a permanent register of political parties and logos, so that the period for declaring lists of candidates could be shortened. Unregistered parties would still be able to take part with a so-called “blank list”.</p><p>Municipalities could also bring forward the deadline for finalising the electoral register, but that would mean more voting cards will be delivered to the wrong address if people move house between the deadline and election day.</p><div class="ad-container overflow-hidden p-4 bg-light my-8 d-none d-md-block"><div class="bg-light p-lg-2 h-100 w-100 d-flex align-items-center justify-content-center position-relative" data-tagname="ROS_Incontent"><div id="div-gpt-ad-dutchnews_ros_incontent" style="display:block;"></div></div></div><div class="ad-container overflow-hidden p-4 bg-light my-8 d-block d-md-none"><div class="bg-light p-lg-2 h-100 w-100 d-flex align-items-center justify-content-center position-relative" data-tagname="ROS_Incontent"><div id="div-gpt-ad-dutchnews_ros_incontent-m" style="display:block;"></div></div></div><p>Bringing forward registration deadlines would also make it more challenging for overseas voters to register in time and send in their ballots. Digital voting would need to be introduced to facilitate this, the electoral council said.</p><p>“It is up to politicians to weigh up the advantages and disadvantages of quicker elections, the possible measures to achieve this and the consequences they will have,” the electoral council said.</p><p>A follow-up advisory report will be published next year following consultations with municipalities, political parties and others involved in organising elections.</p><p>Since 2010 snap elections have become more common, with only one government managing to see out its full term, Mark Rutte’s coalition of VVD and PvdA from 2012 to 2017.</p><p>His third government fell in January 2021, two months short of the finish line, so the election still went ahead on the scheduled date.</p><p>Since then the Netherlands has had caretaker governments for more than half the time, as negotiations to form Mark Rutte’s fourth cabinet and Dick Schoof’s administration lasted nearly eight months only for both cabinets to fall within a year.</p></main><div class="ad-container overflow-hidden d-none d-md-block p-4 bg-light mt-8 mb-10 mx-lg-4"><div class="bg-light p-lg-2 h-100 w-100 d-flex align-items-center justify-content-center position-relative" data-tagname="ROS_Native"><div id="div-gpt-ad-dutchnews_ros_native" style="display:block;"></div></div></div><div class="ad-container overflow-hidden d-block d-md-none bg-light my-8"><div class="bg-light p-lg-2 h-100 w-100 d-flex align-items-center justify-content-center position-relative" data-tagname="ROS_Native"><div id="div-gpt-ad-dutchnews_ros_native-m" style="display:block;"></div></div></div><footer class="my-8 px-4"><div class="pb-8"></div> <a class="btn btn-secondary btn-sm" href="/category/election/?list"></a> <a class="btn btn-secondary btn-sm" href="/category/politics/?list"></a></footer><div class="bg-green-light p-3 mx-4 mt-8 mb-12"></div></article>]]></description><guid>https://www.dutchnews.nl/?p=260643</guid><pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 11:47:43 -0000</pubDate><dc:creator><![CDATA[Gordon Darroch]]></dc:creator></item><item><title>Jumbo family to take full ownership of high street staple Hema</title><link>https://www.dutchnews.nl/2025/12/jumbo-family-to-take-full-ownership-of-high-street-staple-hema/</link><description><![CDATA[<article class="post-260640 post type-post status-publish format-standard has-post-thumbnail hentry category-business category-economy category-retail newsletter-include"><header class="pb-4 px-4"><h1 class="text-serif lh-1"> Jumbo family to take full ownership of high street staple Hema</h1> <time class="text-secondary updated me-2" datetime="2025-12-02T10:20:39+00:00"> December 2, 2025 </time></header><figure aria-describedby="caption-attachment-260641" class="px-lg-5" id="attachment_260641"> <img alt="" class="attachment-full size-full wp-post-image" decoding="async" fetchpriority="high" height="1512" sizes="(max-width: 2016px) 100vw, 2016px" src="/wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2025/12/IMG_9929.jpg" srcset="/wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2025/12/IMG_9929.jpg 2016w, /wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2025/12/IMG_9929-560x420.jpg 560w, /wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2025/12/IMG_9929-1200x900.jpg 1200w, /wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2025/12/IMG_9929-768x576.jpg 768w, /wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2025/12/IMG_9929-1536x1152.jpg 1536w" width="2016"/><figcaption class="px-4 px-lg-0" id="caption-attachment-260641"> A Hema Store in France. Photo: Dutch News</figcaption></figure><main class="px-4"><p data-end="362" data-start="49">Household goods and clothes retail group Hema is set to come entirely under the control of the Van Eerd family’s investment vehicle, which also owns supermarket chain Jumbo.</p><p data-end="362" data-start="49">The family already held a 50% stake in the retailer and will now acquire the remaining shares from Dutch investor Parcom, the two shareholders said in a joint statement on Tuesday. Financial details were not disclosed.</p><p data-end="585" data-start="364">The acquisition still requires approval from the competition watchdog ACM and is subject to advice from Hema’s works council. Hema has a workforce of some 17,000.</p><p data-end="585" data-start="364"><div class="ad-container overflow-hidden p-4 bg-light my-8 d-none d-md-block"><div class="bg-light p-lg-2 h-100 w-100 d-flex align-items-center justify-content-center position-relative" data-tagname="ROS_Inarticle"><div id="div-gpt-ad-dutchnews_ros_inarticle" style="display:block;"></div></div></div><div class="ad-container overflow-hidden p-4 bg-light my-8 d-block d-md-none"><div class="bg-light p-lg-2 h-100 w-100 d-flex align-items-center justify-content-center position-relative" data-tagname="ROS_Inarticle"><div id="div-gpt-ad-dutchnews_ros_inarticle-m" style="display:block;"></div></div></div></p><p data-end="886" data-start="587">Hema recently outlined new growth plans, including upgrading 100 stores and opening 15 new locations in the Netherlands, Belgium and France. The retailer will continue to operate under its own name but will sit fully under the umbrella of the Jumbo family.</p><p data-end="886" data-start="587">“Despite the challenging retail market, Hema is performing strongly. In the first nine months of 2025, we achieved growth in revenue, volume, profit, and customer satisfaction,” chief executive Saskia Egas Reparaz said in a <a href="https://corporate.hema.com/en/hema-continues-growth-strategy-under-full-ownership-of-the-van-eerd-family/">statement</a>.</p><p data-end="1076" data-start="888">The Van Eerd family and Parcom each acquired a <a href="https://www.dutchnews.nl/2020/12/take-over-of-hema-by-jumbo-and-parcom-is-finalised-in-5050-deal/">50% stake in Hema in 2021</a>. Hema had been lumbered with huge debts for years by a variety of different private equity investors and the <a href="https://www.dutchnews.nl/news/2020/04/iconic-dutch-retailer-hema-under-threat-slashes-rent-payments/">coronavirus crisis only made things worse. </a></p><p data-end="1076" data-start="888">Hema stands for <i>Hollandsche Eenheidsprijzen Maatschappij Amsterdam</i> or “Standard Price Company of Holland”. The first Hema opened in Amsterdam in 1926 selling everything you could possibly need for 10, 25 or 50 cents.</p></main><div class="ad-container overflow-hidden d-none d-md-block p-4 bg-light mt-8 mb-10 mx-lg-4"><div class="bg-light p-lg-2 h-100 w-100 d-flex align-items-center justify-content-center position-relative" data-tagname="ROS_Native"><div id="div-gpt-ad-dutchnews_ros_native" style="display:block;"></div></div></div><div class="ad-container overflow-hidden d-block d-md-none bg-light my-8"><div class="bg-light p-lg-2 h-100 w-100 d-flex align-items-center justify-content-center position-relative" data-tagname="ROS_Native"><div id="div-gpt-ad-dutchnews_ros_native-m" style="display:block;"></div></div></div><footer class="my-8 px-4"><div class="pb-8"></div> <a class="btn btn-secondary btn-sm" href="/category/business/?list"></a> <a class="btn btn-secondary btn-sm" href="/category/economy/?list"></a> <a class="btn btn-secondary btn-sm" href="/category/retail/?list"></a></footer><div class="bg-green-light p-3 mx-4 mt-8 mb-12"></div></article>]]></description><guid>https://www.dutchnews.nl/?p=260640</guid><pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 10:20:39 -0000</pubDate><dc:creator><![CDATA[Robin Pascoe]]></dc:creator></item><item><title>Descendants of Suriname’s enslaved people accept king’s apology</title><link>https://www.dutchnews.nl/2025/12/descendants-of-surinames-enslaved-people-accept-kings-apology/</link><description><![CDATA[<article class="post-260637 post type-post status-publish format-standard has-post-thumbnail hentry category-colonialism category-royals category-slavery category-suriname"><header class="pb-4 px-4"><h1 class="text-serif lh-1"> Descendants of Suriname’s enslaved people accept king’s apology</h1> <time class="text-secondary updated me-2" datetime="2025-12-02T10:04:38+00:00"> December 2, 2025 </time></header><figure aria-describedby="caption-attachment-260638" class="px-lg-5" id="attachment_260638"> <img alt="" class="attachment-full size-full wp-post-image" decoding="async" fetchpriority="high" height="726" sizes="(max-width: 1000px) 100vw, 1000px" src="/wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2025/12/ANP-543612506.jpg" srcset="/wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2025/12/ANP-543612506.jpg 1000w, /wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2025/12/ANP-543612506-560x407.jpg 560w, /wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2025/12/ANP-543612506-768x558.jpg 768w" width="1000"/><figcaption class="px-4 px-lg-0" id="caption-attachment-260638"> King Willem-Alexander and queen Máxima speak with the descendants of slaves. Photo: Remko de Waal ANP</figcaption></figure><main class="px-4"><div class="relative basis-auto flex-col -mb-(--composer-overlap-px) [--composer-overlap-px:28px] grow flex overflow-hidden"><div class="relative h-full"><div class="flex h-full flex-col overflow-y-auto thread-xl:pt-(--header-height) [scrollbar-gutter:stable_both-edges]"><div class="flex flex-col text-sm thread-xl:pt-header-height pb-25"><article class="text-token-text-primary w-full focus:outline-none [--shadow-height:45px] has-data-writing-block:pointer-events-none has-data-writing-block:-mt-(--shadow-height) has-data-writing-block:pt-(--shadow-height) [&amp;:has([data-writing-block])&gt;*]:pointer-events-auto scroll-mt-[calc(var(--header-height)+min(200px,max(70px,20svh)))]" data-scroll-anchor="true" data-testid="conversation-turn-18" data-turn="assistant" data-turn-id="request-WEB:b5b10e03-12ac-4b53-b1e3-c2b50b407754-8" dir="auto" tabindex="-1"><div class="text-base my-auto mx-auto pb-10 [--thread-content-margin:--spacing(4)] thread-sm:[--thread-content-margin:--spacing(6)] thread-lg:[--thread-content-margin:--spacing(16)] px-(--thread-content-margin)"><div class="[--thread-content-max-width:40rem] thread-lg:[--thread-content-max-width:48rem] mx-auto max-w-(--thread-content-max-width) flex-1 group/turn-messages focus-visible:outline-hidden relative flex w-full min-w-0 flex-col agent-turn" tabindex="-1"><div class="flex max-w-full flex-col grow"><div class="min-h-8 text-message relative flex w-full flex-col items-end gap-2 text-start break-words whitespace-normal [.text-message+&amp;]:mt-1" data-message-author-role="assistant" data-message-id="86e468b0-6e12-450f-8843-3506d82b08f1" data-message-model-slug="gpt-5-1" dir="auto"><div class="flex w-full flex-col gap-1 empty:hidden first:pt-[1px]"><div class="markdown prose dark:prose-invert w-full break-words light markdown-new-styling"><p data-end="241" data-start="78">Dutch king Willem-Alexander has formally apologised for the Netherlands’ role in slavery during the first state visit to the former colony of Suriname in 47 years.</p><p data-end="390" data-start="243">The king met descendants of enslaved people and representatives of Indigenous communities behind closed doors on Monday, the first day of the royal visit.</p><p data-end="617" data-start="392">The group had requested a conversation with the king following his apology during national commemorations marking the end of slavery on July 1, 2023. At that time, the king also asked for forgiveness and acknowledged that his ancestors had failed to act against the system of slavery.</p><p data-end="617" data-start="392"><div class="ad-container overflow-hidden p-4 bg-light my-8 d-none d-md-block"><div class="bg-light p-lg-2 h-100 w-100 d-flex align-items-center justify-content-center position-relative" data-tagname="ROS_Inarticle"><div id="div-gpt-ad-dutchnews_ros_inarticle" style="display:block;"></div></div></div><div class="ad-container overflow-hidden p-4 bg-light my-8 d-block d-md-none"><div class="bg-light p-lg-2 h-100 w-100 d-flex align-items-center justify-content-center position-relative" data-tagname="ROS_Inarticle"><div id="div-gpt-ad-dutchnews_ros_inarticle-m" style="display:block;"></div></div></div></p><p data-end="1033" data-start="755">Hesdy Ommen, chairman of the Federatie van Para Plantages, accepted the king’s apology on behalf of the group. “I accepted the apology and offered forgiveness on behalf of all the leaders,” he is reported as saying by news agency ANP. “From this point we must build on what comes next.”</p><p data-end="1033" data-start="755">After the meeting, Suriname’s president Jennifer Simons said the country now wants to start talks with the Netherlands about the recovery programme, for which €66 million was set aside in 2023.</p><p>Suriname, she said, should have a leading role in shaping and carrying out that programme. “The €66 million is not reparations according to the Surinamese government, and as far as I understand the Dutch government also sees it as a gesture,” she said.</p><p data-end="1033" data-start="755"><div class="ad-container overflow-hidden p-4 bg-light my-8 d-none d-md-block"><div class="bg-light p-lg-2 h-100 w-100 d-flex align-items-center justify-content-center position-relative" data-tagname="ROS_Incontent"><div id="div-gpt-ad-dutchnews_ros_incontent" style="display:block;"></div></div></div><div class="ad-container overflow-hidden p-4 bg-light my-8 d-block d-md-none"><div class="bg-light p-lg-2 h-100 w-100 d-flex align-items-center justify-content-center position-relative" data-tagname="ROS_Incontent"><div id="div-gpt-ad-dutchnews_ros_incontent-m" style="display:block;"></div></div></div></p><p data-end="1366" data-start="1035">The formal apology by the king in 2023 and prime minister in 2022 led to a string of measures and the establishment of a €200 million fund to raise “knowledge and awareness” and to combat racism.</p><p data-end="1366" data-start="1035">The descendants of enslaved people can change their surnames free of charge. Tula, who led the slave population in Curaçao in an uprising against the Dutch colonial government in 1795, has been rehabilitated and Amsterdam is to host a museum dedicated to slavery.</p><p data-end="2019" data-is-last-node="" data-is-only-node="" data-start="1745">Slavery was formally abolished in the former colonies of Suriname and the Dutch Antilles on July 1, 1863, ending a period of around 200 years.</p><p data-end="2019" data-is-last-node="" data-is-only-node="" data-start="1745">However, enslaved people in Suriname were only fully freed in 1873, since the law stipulated a mandatory 10-year transition period. Suriname was declared independent on November 25, 1975.</p></div></div></div></div></div></div></article></div></div></div></div></main><div class="ad-container overflow-hidden d-none d-md-block p-4 bg-light mt-8 mb-10 mx-lg-4"><div class="bg-light p-lg-2 h-100 w-100 d-flex align-items-center justify-content-center position-relative" data-tagname="ROS_Native"><div id="div-gpt-ad-dutchnews_ros_native" style="display:block;"></div></div></div><div class="ad-container overflow-hidden d-block d-md-none bg-light my-8"><div class="bg-light p-lg-2 h-100 w-100 d-flex align-items-center justify-content-center position-relative" data-tagname="ROS_Native"><div id="div-gpt-ad-dutchnews_ros_native-m" style="display:block;"></div></div></div><footer class="my-8 px-4"><div class="pb-8"></div> <a class="btn btn-secondary btn-sm" href="/category/colonialism/?list"></a> <a class="btn btn-secondary btn-sm" href="/category/royals/?list"></a> <a class="btn btn-secondary btn-sm" href="/category/slavery/?list"></a> <a class="btn btn-secondary btn-sm" href="/category/suriname/?list"></a></footer><div class="bg-green-light p-3 mx-4 mt-8 mb-12"></div></article>]]></description><guid>https://www.dutchnews.nl/?p=260637</guid><pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 10:04:38 -0000</pubDate><dc:creator><![CDATA[Robin Pascoe]]></dc:creator></item></channel></rss>