<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>DutchNews.nl</title><link>https://www.dutchnews.nl/</link><description>DutchNews.nl brings daily news from The Netherlands in English</description><lastBuildDate>Sun, 18 Jan 2026 20:45:08 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>PSV go 16 points clear as Feyenoord and Ajax drop points again</title><link>https://www.dutchnews.nl/2026/01/psv-go-16-points-clear-as-feyenoord-and-ajax-drop-points-again/</link><description><![CDATA[<article class="post-262367 post type-post status-publish format-standard has-post-thumbnail hentry category-eredivisie category-football category-sport"><header class="pb-4 px-4"><h1 class="text-serif lh-1"> PSV go 16 points clear as Feyenoord and Ajax drop points again</h1> <time class="text-secondary updated me-2" datetime="2026-01-18T20:45:08+00:00"> January 18, 2026 </time></header><figure aria-describedby="caption-attachment-262369" class="px-lg-5" id="attachment_262369"> <img alt="" class="attachment-full size-full wp-post-image" decoding="async" fetchpriority="high" height="1707" sizes="(max-width: 2560px) 100vw, 2560px" src="/wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/ANP-547913321-scaled.jpg" srcset="/wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/ANP-547913321-scaled.jpg 2560w, /wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/ANP-547913321-560x373.jpg 560w, /wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/ANP-547913321-1200x800.jpg 1200w, /wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/ANP-547913321-360x240.jpg 360w, /wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/ANP-547913321-768x512.jpg 768w, /wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/ANP-547913321-1536x1024.jpg 1536w, /wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/ANP-547913321-2048x1365.jpg 2048w" width="2560"/><figcaption class="px-4 px-lg-0" id="caption-attachment-262369"> Quinten Timber is expected to leave Feyenoord after his public spat with coach Robin van Persie. Photo: ANP/Bart Stoutjesdijk</figcaption></figure><main class="px-4"><p>PSV extended their lead in the Eredivisie to 16 points after Feyenoord lost a dramatic Rotterdam derby to Sparta, despite coming back from 3-1 down in the closing minutes.</p><p>Feyenoord were without the league’s top scorer Ayase Ueda, who was struggling for fitness, as they <a href="https://nos.nl/artikel/2598744-nieuwe-nederlaag-feyenoord-ondanks-hakbal-en-omhaal-van-persie-junior">took on their city rivals in De Kuip</a> looking for their first win since December 6.</p><p>Sparta took the lead at the end of the first half when Joshua Kitolano swapped passes with Tobias Lauritsen on the edge of the area before firing into the top corner. Ten minutes after the restart Mitchell van Bergen added a second when he caught Tsuyoshi Watanabe dawdling on the ball in his own penalty area.</p><div class="ad-container overflow-hidden p-4 bg-light my-8 d-none d-md-block"><div class="bg-light p-lg-2 h-100 w-100 d-flex align-items-center justify-content-center position-relative" data-tagname="ROS_Inarticle"><div id="div-gpt-ad-dutchnews_ros_inarticle" style="display:block;"></div></div></div><div class="ad-container overflow-hidden p-4 bg-light my-8 d-block d-md-none"><div class="bg-light p-lg-2 h-100 w-100 d-flex align-items-center justify-content-center position-relative" data-tagname="ROS_Inarticle"><div id="div-gpt-ad-dutchnews_ros_inarticle-m" style="display:block;"></div></div></div><p>Feyenoord midfielder In-boem Hwang reduced the deficit with a long-range shot, but more slack defending allowed Shunsuke Mito to slide in Sparta’s third with 20 minutes to play.</p><p>Shaqueel van Persie, sent on by his father Robin to boost the attack, showed his father’s poacher’s instincts with two magnificent flicks of his boot to score in the 87th and 88th minutes, but Kitolano silenced the Feyenoord cheers with his second in injury time.</p><p>Dutch international midfielder Quinten Timber looks to have played his last match for Feyenoord after <a href="https://nos.nl/artikel/2598762-timber-haalt-uit-naar-van-persie-die-terugbijt-en-van-geen-opstappen-wil-weten">clashing publicly with Robin van Persie</a>. Van Persie said there was no way back for Timber, who was dropped against Sparta, after the player told ESPN he was disappointed by the coach’s criticism of his recent performances.</p><h2>Fragile Ajax</h2><p>PSV <a href="https://nos.nl/artikel/2598623-psv-wint-door-late-treffer-perisic-bij-fortuna-sittard-vijftiende-uitzege-op-rij">needed a late goal by veteran midfielder Ivan Perisic</a> to book their 15th consecutive victory at Fortuna Sittard. Paul Wanner put the visitors ahead after just eight minutes, only for Kaj Sierhuis to level the scores with a long-range strike four minutes later.</p><p>Third-placed Ajax also dropped points as they let a two-goal lead slip at home to Go Ahead Eagles.</p><p>Goals by Davy Klaassen and Kasper Dolberg gave the Amsterdammers an apparently comfortable lead in a first half when they could have scored five.</p><div class="ad-container overflow-hidden p-4 bg-light my-8 d-none d-md-block"><div class="bg-light p-lg-2 h-100 w-100 d-flex align-items-center justify-content-center position-relative" data-tagname="ROS_Incontent"><div id="div-gpt-ad-dutchnews_ros_incontent" style="display:block;"></div></div></div><div class="ad-container overflow-hidden p-4 bg-light my-8 d-block d-md-none"><div class="bg-light p-lg-2 h-100 w-100 d-flex align-items-center justify-content-center position-relative" data-tagname="ROS_Incontent"><div id="div-gpt-ad-dutchnews_ros_incontent-m" style="display:block;"></div></div></div><p>But Ajax’s fragile nerves were exposed when Thibo Baeten rounded off a well-worked move with a diagonal shot after 53 minutes, before Milan Smit levelled with a spectacular volley on the spin.</p><p>NEC closed the gap on Ajax to two points as they claimed all three points from a <a href="https://nos.nl/artikel/2598638-nec-wint-knotsgek-duel-bij-nac-en-voert-de-druk-op-ajax-op">helter-skelter match against NAC</a>.</p><p>NEC went two goals up in the first 16 minutes, but a double by NAC’s French striker Moussa Soumano, the first a glorious curling shot from 25 metres, squared the scores after 55 minutes.</p><p>Dirk Proper put NEC back in front after a clever stepover by Tjaronn Chery, before Boy Kemper smashed in another equaliser. But NEC were not to be denied as Kodai Sano swept home the winner in the fourth minute of injury time,</p><h2>Visitors win derbies</h2><p>Groningen <a href="https://nos.nl/artikel/2598695-hoofdrol-invaldoelman-jurjus-bij-groningse-zege-in-heerenveen">prevailed 2-0 in the derby of the north</a> as Heerenveen’s goalkeeper Bernt Klaverboer turned a cross by Younes Taha into his own net, before Thijmen Blokzijl charged through the centre of defence to add a second.</p><p>Twente <a href="https://nos.nl/artikel/2598718-twente-wint-verhitte-derby-bij-heracles-met-rode-kaart-en-onderbreking">won the derby of the east at Heracles</a> by the same scoreline in a match that was interrupted for 10 minutes when a ball-boy threw a plastic beaker at Twente midfielder Ramiz Zerrouki.</p><p>Zerrouki was later sent off for swinging his arm at Heracles’ Ajdin Hrustic, a decision that was slammed by Twente’s coach John van den Brom because Hrustic was pulling Zerrouki’s shirt at the time.</p><p>Twente had just gone 2-0 up through a Ricky van Wolfswinkel penalty, adding to Thomas van der Belt’s first-half header, but Heracles were unable to benefit from the extra man.</p><h2>Volendam move up</h2><p>Volendam followed up their midweek cup success by moving out of the bottom three with <a href="https://nos.nl/artikel/2598717-volendam-klimt-met-knappe-overwinning-op-utrecht-uit-degradatiezone">a 2-1 win against Utrecht,</a> who failed to win for the sixth league match in a row.</p><p>Joel Ideho put Volendam ahead with a curling shot into the top corner before Brandley Kuwas, standing in for the injured Henk Veerman, waltzed through the Utrecht defence to add a second shortly before half-time.</p><p>The basement battle between Excelsior and Telstar <a href="https://nos.nl/artikel/2598717-volendam-klimt-met-knappe-overwinning-op-utrecht-uit-degradatiezone">ended all square</a> as Telstar surrendered a two-goal lead in the last 15 minutes. Noah Naujoks claimed the equaliser as he outjumped goalkeeper Ronald Koeman to nod in a deflected high cross.</p><p>AZ were unable to keep up the momentum from their 6-0 cup win against Ajax as they <a href="https://nos.nl/artikel/2598621-az-kan-monsterzege-op-ajax-geen-passend-vervolg-geven-3-1-nederlaag-bij-pec">lost 3-1 at PEC Zwolle</a>, with Shola Shoretire scoring twice for the hosts, while AZ’s Peer Koopmeiners found the net directly from a corner.</p><p><strong>Results</strong></p><p><strong>Saturday</strong></p><p>Ajax 2-2 Go Ahead Eagles</p><p>Excelsior 2-2 Telstar</p><p>Fortuna Sittard 1-2 PSV Eindhoven</p><p>NEC Nijmegen 4-3 NAC Breda</p><p>PEC Zwolle 3-1 AZ Alkmaar</p><p><strong>Sunday</strong></p><p>Feyenoord 3-4 Sparta Rotterdam</p><p>Heerenveen 0-2 Groningen</p><p>Heracles Almelo 0-2 Twente Enschede</p><p>Volendam 2-1 Utrecht</p></main><div class="ad-container overflow-hidden d-none d-md-block p-4 bg-light mt-8 mb-10 mx-lg-4"><div class="bg-light p-lg-2 h-100 w-100 d-flex align-items-center justify-content-center position-relative" data-tagname="ROS_Native"><div id="div-gpt-ad-dutchnews_ros_native" style="display:block;"></div></div></div><div class="ad-container overflow-hidden d-block d-md-none bg-light my-8"><div class="bg-light p-lg-2 h-100 w-100 d-flex align-items-center justify-content-center position-relative" data-tagname="ROS_Native"><div id="div-gpt-ad-dutchnews_ros_native-m" style="display:block;"></div></div></div><footer class="my-8 px-4"><div class="pb-8"></div> <a class="btn btn-secondary btn-sm" href="/category/football/eredivisie/?list"></a> <a class="btn btn-secondary btn-sm" href="/category/football/?list"></a> <a class="btn btn-secondary btn-sm" href="/category/sport/?list"></a></footer><div class="bg-green-light p-3 mx-4 mt-8 mb-12"></div></article>]]></description><guid>https://www.dutchnews.nl/?p=262367</guid><pubDate>Sun, 18 Jan 2026 20:45:08 -0000</pubDate><dc:creator><![CDATA[Gordon Darroch]]></dc:creator></item><item><title>Trump’s Greenland tariffs are “blackmail”, says Dutch minister</title><link>https://www.dutchnews.nl/2026/01/trumps-greenland-tariffs-are-blackmail-says-dutch-minister/</link><description><![CDATA[<article class="post-262362 post type-post status-publish format-standard has-post-thumbnail hentry category-armed-forces category-dutch-european-news category-foreign-affairs category-greenland category-us"><header class="pb-4 px-4"><h1 class="text-serif lh-1"> Trump’s Greenland tariffs are “blackmail”, says Dutch minister</h1> <time class="text-secondary updated me-2" datetime="2026-01-18T10:37:07+00:00"> January 18, 2026 </time></header><figure aria-describedby="caption-attachment-262364" class="px-lg-5" id="attachment_262364"> <img alt="" class="attachment-full size-full wp-post-image" decoding="async" fetchpriority="high" height="667" sizes="(max-width: 1000px) 100vw, 1000px" src="/wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/ANP-547847930.jpg" srcset="/wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/ANP-547847930.jpg 1000w, /wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/ANP-547847930-560x374.jpg 560w, /wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/ANP-547847930-360x240.jpg 360w, /wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/ANP-547847930-768x512.jpg 768w" width="1000"/><figcaption class="px-4 px-lg-0" id="caption-attachment-262364"> Protests against Trump's Greenland takeover plan. Photo:  Alessandro Rampazzo AFP</figcaption></figure><main class="px-4"><p data-end="349" data-start="116">Dutch foreign minister David van Weel on Sunday described plans by US president Donald Trump to impose tariffs on eight European countries because of their support for Greenland as “blackmail”, “incomprehensible” and “inappropriate”.</p><p data-end="504" data-start="351">Speaking on the television current affairs show WNL op Zondag, Van Weel said efforts now have to be made to make sure “this ridiculous plan” is scrapped.</p><p data-end="856" data-is-last-node="" data-is-only-node="" data-start="506">“This is blackmail and it is not the way to work with your allies,” the minister said.</p><p data-end="856" data-is-last-node="" data-is-only-node="" data-start="506">The Netherlands, he said, does not plan to recall the two people it has sent to the Arctic island to take part in the preparations for a Nato exercise, despite the threats. And once the actual operation starts, the Netherlands will send more soldiers to join in, but how many has not yet been decided.</p><p data-end="856" data-is-last-node="" data-is-only-node="" data-start="506"><div class="ad-container overflow-hidden p-4 bg-light my-8 d-none d-md-block"><div class="bg-light p-lg-2 h-100 w-100 d-flex align-items-center justify-content-center position-relative" data-tagname="ROS_Inarticle"><div id="div-gpt-ad-dutchnews_ros_inarticle" style="display:block;"></div></div></div><div class="ad-container overflow-hidden p-4 bg-light my-8 d-block d-md-none"><div class="bg-light p-lg-2 h-100 w-100 d-flex align-items-center justify-content-center position-relative" data-tagname="ROS_Inarticle"><div id="div-gpt-ad-dutchnews_ros_inarticle-m" style="display:block;"></div></div></div></p><p data-end="856" data-is-last-node="" data-is-only-node="" data-start="506">European leaders will travel to Davos in Switzerland this week for the World Economic Forum and Trump is also expected to attend. “We have a lot of homework to do there,” Van Weel said. “And the first priority is to get this ridiculous proposal off the table.”</p><h2 data-end="856" data-start="506">Europe</h2><p data-end="663" data-start="272">The European Commission has warned the move threatens to undermine relations between the United States and Europe with commission president <a href="https://x.com/vonderleyen/status/2012608782593827232"><span class="hover:entity-accent entity-underline inline cursor-pointer align-baseline"><span class="whitespace-normal">Ursula von der Leyen</span></span></a> saying the 10% tariffs announced by Trump risk triggering “a dangerous downward spiral”.</p><p data-end="663" data-start="272">The Danish mission, she said, had been coordinated in advance and was aimed at strengthening security in the Arctic.</p><p data-end="901" data-start="665">Trump said on his social media platform <a href="https://x.com/TheWarPolitics0/status/2012584129250910716/photo/1">Truth Social</a> that the tariffs will apply from February 1 to all goods from countries sending troops to Greenland. If Greenland has not been “bought” by June, he said, the tariffs will rise to 25%.</p><p data-end="1618" data-start="1215">Defence minister Ruben Brekelmans announced earlier this week that the Netherlands is sending two military personnel to Greenland as part of the Danish mission, which is seen as preparation for a possible Nato exercise.</p><p data-end="1618" data-start="1215"><div class="ad-container overflow-hidden p-4 bg-light my-8 d-none d-md-block"><div class="bg-light p-lg-2 h-100 w-100 d-flex align-items-center justify-content-center position-relative" data-tagname="ROS_Incontent"><div id="div-gpt-ad-dutchnews_ros_incontent" style="display:block;"></div></div></div><div class="ad-container overflow-hidden p-4 bg-light my-8 d-block d-md-none"><div class="bg-light p-lg-2 h-100 w-100 d-flex align-items-center justify-content-center position-relative" data-tagname="ROS_Incontent"><div id="div-gpt-ad-dutchnews_ros_incontent-m" style="display:block;"></div></div></div></p><p data-end="1955" data-start="1620">Dutch MPs have also been quick to condemn the tariffs. ChristenUnie MP <a href="https://x.com/Pieter_Grinwis/status/2012589997765881923">Pieter Grinwis</a> called the move “bizarre”, while GroenLinks-PvdA leader <a href="https://x.com/jesseklaver/status/2012585358244933873">Jesse Klaver</a> accused the US of blackmail, saying the move demands a “robust response” from Europe.</p><p data-end="1955" data-start="1620"><span class="css-1jxf684 r-bcqeeo r-1ttztb7 r-qvutc0 r-poiln3">CDA parliamentarian <a href="https://x.com/DerkBoswijk/status/2012573627791692030">Derk Boswijk</a> said the Netherlands is participating in the reconnaissance mission in Greenland “because it takes the security concerns of its Nato ally, the United States, in the Arctic region seriously.”</span></p><p data-end="1955" data-start="1620"><span class="css-1jxf684 r-bcqeeo r-1ttztb7 r-qvutc0 r-poiln3">“In that context, responding with tariffs would be highly illogical,” Boswijk said.</span></p><h2 data-end="1955" data-start="1620">Exports</h2><p data-end="2259" data-start="1957">Dutch businesses also warned of serious economic damage if the tariffs go ahead. Exporters’ association <a href="https://www.transport-online.nl/114298/evofenedex-heffingen-slecht-voor-handelsrelatie-met-vs/">Evofenedex</a> said the tariffs are “very harmful” for companies trading with the US, creating uncertainty over whether to continue exporting or look for alternative markets.</p><p data-end="2593" data-start="2261">In 2024, the Netherlands exported more than €38 billion worth of goods to the US, nearly 6% of total exports, while imports from the US totalled almost €60 billion.</p><p data-end="3029" data-start="2595">Within Europe, criticism was outspoken. Swedish prime minister <span class="hover:entity-accent entity-underline inline cursor-pointer align-baseline"><span class="whitespace-normal">Ulf Kristersson</span></span> said Europe “will not be blackmailed”, while French president <span class="hover:entity-accent entity-underline inline cursor-pointer align-baseline"><span class="whitespace-normal">Emmanuel Macron</span></span> called the tariffs “unacceptable” and said no intimidation would influence France.</p><p data-end="3029" data-start="2595">British prime minister <span class="hover:entity-accent entity-underline inline cursor-pointer align-baseline"><span class="whitespace-normal">Keir Starmer</span></span> said imposing tariffs on allies pursuing collective Nato security was “completely wrong”.</p><h2 data-end="3029" data-start="2595">Retaliation</h2><p data-end="3373" data-start="3031">Some have already called for the <span class="css-1jxf684 r-bcqeeo r-1ttztb7 r-qvutc0 r-poiln3">recently agreed EU–US. trade deal to be put on hold because of the US threat.</span></p><p data-end="3373" data-start="3031">Dutch MEP <span class="hover:entity-accent entity-underline inline cursor-pointer align-baseline"><span class="whitespace-normal">Bart Groothuis</span></span> said the EU should be prepared to respond more forcefully, including by deploying the bloc’s anti-coercion instrument, which could target US companies through trade restrictions, public procurement bans or limits on intellectual property rights. “At some point we have to draw a line,” he said.</p><p data-end="3684" data-start="3375">The commander of the Dutch armed forces <span class="hover:entity-accent entity-underline inline cursor-pointer align-baseline"><span class="whitespace-normal">Onno Eichelsheim</span></span> warned that escalating tensions risk creating a rift within Nato. “That plays into Putin’s hands,” he told Nieuwsuur on Saturday.</p><p data-end="3889" data-is-last-node="" data-is-only-node="" data-start="3686">EU member states are due to discuss the US tariffs collectively on Sunday afternoon.</p></main><div class="ad-container overflow-hidden d-none d-md-block p-4 bg-light mt-8 mb-10 mx-lg-4"><div class="bg-light p-lg-2 h-100 w-100 d-flex align-items-center justify-content-center position-relative" data-tagname="ROS_Native"><div id="div-gpt-ad-dutchnews_ros_native" style="display:block;"></div></div></div><div class="ad-container overflow-hidden d-block d-md-none bg-light my-8"><div class="bg-light p-lg-2 h-100 w-100 d-flex align-items-center justify-content-center position-relative" data-tagname="ROS_Native"><div id="div-gpt-ad-dutchnews_ros_native-m" style="display:block;"></div></div></div><footer class="my-8 px-4"><div class="pb-8"></div> <a class="btn btn-secondary btn-sm" href="/category/armed-forces/?list"></a> <a class="btn btn-secondary btn-sm" href="/category/dutch-european-news/?list"></a> <a class="btn btn-secondary btn-sm" href="/category/foreign-affairs/?list"></a> <a class="btn btn-secondary btn-sm" href="/category/greenland/?list"></a> <a class="btn btn-secondary btn-sm" href="/category/us/?list"></a></footer><div class="bg-green-light p-3 mx-4 mt-8 mb-12"></div></article>]]></description><guid>https://www.dutchnews.nl/?p=262362</guid><pubDate>Sun, 18 Jan 2026 10:37:07 -0000</pubDate><dc:creator><![CDATA[Robin Pascoe]]></dc:creator></item><item><title>Local elections on March 18:  thousands of foreigners can vote</title><link>https://www.dutchnews.nl/2026/01/local-elections-on-march-18-thousands-of-foreigners-can-vote/</link><description><![CDATA[<article class="post-262359 post type-post status-publish format-standard has-post-thumbnail hentry category-election category-local-government category-politics"><header class="pb-4 px-4"><h1 class="text-serif lh-1"> Local elections on March 18:  thousands of foreigners can vote</h1> <time class="text-secondary updated me-2" datetime="2026-01-18T09:50:05+00:00"> January 18, 2026 </time></header><figure aria-describedby="caption-attachment-227305" class="px-lg-5" id="attachment_227305"> <img alt="" class="attachment-full size-full wp-post-image" decoding="async" fetchpriority="high" height="1920" sizes="(max-width: 2560px) 100vw, 2560px" src="/wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/PB220025-scaled.jpg" srcset="/wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/PB220025-scaled.jpg 2560w, /wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/PB220025-560x420.jpg 560w, /wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/PB220025-1200x900.jpg 1200w, /wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/PB220025-768x576.jpg 768w, /wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/PB220025-1536x1152.jpg 1536w, /wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/PB220025-2048x1536.jpg 2048w" width="2560"/><figcaption class="px-4 px-lg-0" id="caption-attachment-227305"> Photo: Dutch News</figcaption></figure><main class="px-4"><p>On March 18, the Netherlands will hold new elections – this time to elect members of the country’s 342 local councils. Unlike in the national elections, people from EU countries will be able to vote, as will non-EU nationals who have lived in the Netherlands for five years.</p><p>Dutch News will be reporting on the campaigns, the big issues and on efforts to involve the international community in the vote. To kick off, please take part in this short survey.</p><p><iframe frameborder="0" height="5159" marginheight="0" marginwidth="0" src="https://docs.google.com/forms/d/e/1FAIpQLSd8WkEgCWT3qrzwJgFlzwWVZVGG_vCyCh5xo2BnL_d6milfLg/viewform?embedded=true" width="600">Loading…</iframe></p></main><div class="ad-container overflow-hidden d-none d-md-block p-4 bg-light mt-8 mb-10 mx-lg-4"><div class="bg-light p-lg-2 h-100 w-100 d-flex align-items-center justify-content-center position-relative" data-tagname="ROS_Native"><div id="div-gpt-ad-dutchnews_ros_native" style="display:block;"></div></div></div><div class="ad-container overflow-hidden d-block d-md-none bg-light my-8"><div class="bg-light p-lg-2 h-100 w-100 d-flex align-items-center justify-content-center position-relative" data-tagname="ROS_Native"><div id="div-gpt-ad-dutchnews_ros_native-m" style="display:block;"></div></div></div><footer class="my-8 px-4"><div class="pb-8"></div> <a class="btn btn-secondary btn-sm" href="/category/election/?list"></a> <a class="btn btn-secondary btn-sm" href="/category/local-government/?list"></a> <a class="btn btn-secondary btn-sm" href="/category/politics/?list"></a></footer><div class="bg-green-light p-3 mx-4 mt-8 mb-12"></div></article>]]></description><guid>https://www.dutchnews.nl/?p=262359</guid><pubDate>Sun, 18 Jan 2026 09:50:05 -0000</pubDate><dc:creator><![CDATA[Robin Pascoe]]></dc:creator></item><item><title>Dutch MPs, businesses, slam Trump’s “bizarre” Greenland tariffs</title><link>https://www.dutchnews.nl/2026/01/dutch-mps-businesses-slam-trumps-bizarre-greenland-tariffs/</link><description><![CDATA[<article class="post-262354 post type-post status-publish format-standard has-post-thumbnail hentry category-dutch-european-news category-foreign-affairs category-greenland category-nato category-us"><header class="pb-4 px-4"><h1 class="text-serif lh-1"> Dutch MPs, businesses, slam Trump’s “bizarre” Greenland tariffs</h1> <time class="text-secondary updated me-2" datetime="2026-01-18T09:12:07+00:00"> January 18, 2026 </time></header><figure aria-describedby="caption-attachment-262355" class="px-lg-5" id="attachment_262355"> <img alt="" class="attachment-full size-full wp-post-image" decoding="async" fetchpriority="high" height="566" sizes="(max-width: 1000px) 100vw, 1000px" src="/wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/ANP-547848736.jpg" srcset="/wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/ANP-547848736.jpg 1000w, /wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/ANP-547848736-560x317.jpg 560w, /wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/ANP-547848736-768x435.jpg 768w" width="1000"/><figcaption class="px-4 px-lg-0" id="caption-attachment-262355"> Protestors against the US threat on Greenland on Saturday. Photo: 
Mads Schmidt Rasmussen / HO / Arctic Creative / AFP</figcaption></figure><main class="px-4"><p data-end="270" data-start="0">Dutch and European politicians have reacted angrily to the decision by US president <span class="hover:entity-accent entity-underline inline cursor-pointer align-baseline"><span class="whitespace-normal">Donald Trump</span></span> to impose import tariffs on eight European countries, <a href="https://www.dutchnews.nl/2026/01/nl-among-countries-hit-by-trump-tariffs-for-support-of-greenland/">including the Netherlands</a>, over their participation in a Danish military mission on Greenland.</p><p data-end="663" data-start="272">The European Commission warned the move threatens to undermine relations between the United States and Europe with commission president <a href="https://x.com/vonderleyen/status/2012608782593827232"><span class="hover:entity-accent entity-underline inline cursor-pointer align-baseline"><span class="whitespace-normal">Ursula von der Leyen</span></span></a> saying the 10% tariffs announced by Trump risk triggering “a dangerous downward spiral”.</p><p data-end="663" data-start="272">The Danish mission, she said, had been coordinated in advance and was aimed at strengthening security in the Arctic.</p><p data-end="663" data-start="272"><div class="ad-container overflow-hidden p-4 bg-light my-8 d-none d-md-block"><div class="bg-light p-lg-2 h-100 w-100 d-flex align-items-center justify-content-center position-relative" data-tagname="ROS_Inarticle"><div id="div-gpt-ad-dutchnews_ros_inarticle" style="display:block;"></div></div></div><div class="ad-container overflow-hidden p-4 bg-light my-8 d-block d-md-none"><div class="bg-light p-lg-2 h-100 w-100 d-flex align-items-center justify-content-center position-relative" data-tagname="ROS_Inarticle"><div id="div-gpt-ad-dutchnews_ros_inarticle-m" style="display:block;"></div></div></div></p><p data-end="901" data-start="665">Trump said on his social media platform <a href="https://x.com/TheWarPolitics0/status/2012584129250910716/photo/1">Truth Social</a> that the tariffs will apply from February 1 to all goods from countries sending troops to Greenland. If Greenland has not been “bought” by June, he said, the tariffs will rise to 25%.</p><p data-end="1618" data-start="1215">Defence minister Ruben Brekelmans announced earlier this week that the Netherlands is sending two military personnel to Greenland as part of the Danish mission, which is seen as preparation for a possible Nato exercise.</p><p data-end="1618" data-start="1215">France, the United Kingdom, Germany, Finland, Sweden and Norway are also taking part. Belgium is <a href="https://www.politico.eu/article/belgium-rejects-clash-with-uncle-sam-europe-steps-up-greenland-presence-theo-francken/">sending one soldier</a> but was not mentioned by Trump among the countries facing tariffs.</p><p data-end="1618" data-start="1215"><div class="ad-container overflow-hidden p-4 bg-light my-8 d-none d-md-block"><div class="bg-light p-lg-2 h-100 w-100 d-flex align-items-center justify-content-center position-relative" data-tagname="ROS_Incontent"><div id="div-gpt-ad-dutchnews_ros_incontent" style="display:block;"></div></div></div><div class="ad-container overflow-hidden p-4 bg-light my-8 d-block d-md-none"><div class="bg-light p-lg-2 h-100 w-100 d-flex align-items-center justify-content-center position-relative" data-tagname="ROS_Incontent"><div id="div-gpt-ad-dutchnews_ros_incontent-m" style="display:block;"></div></div></div></p><p data-end="1618" data-start="1215">Caretaker foreign minister <span class="hover:entity-accent entity-underline inline cursor-pointer align-baseline"><span class="whitespace-normal">David van Weel</span></span> said he had “taken note” of Trump’s announcement and was in close contact with European partners. The Arctic mission, he said, was aimed at strengthening security in the area.</p><p data-end="1955" data-start="1620">MPs were quick to condemn the tariffs. ChristenUnie MP <a href="https://x.com/Pieter_Grinwis/status/2012589997765881923">Pieter Grinwis</a> called the move “bizarre”, while GroenLinks-PvdA leader <a href="https://x.com/jesseklaver/status/2012585358244933873">Jesse Klaver</a> accused the US of blackmail, saying the move demands a “robust response” from Europe.</p><p data-end="1955" data-start="1620"><span class="css-1jxf684 r-bcqeeo r-1ttztb7 r-qvutc0 r-poiln3">CDA parliamentarian <a href="https://x.com/DerkBoswijk/status/2012573627791692030">Derk Boswijk</a> said the Netherlands is participating in the reconnaissance mission in Greenland “because it takes the security concerns of its Nato ally, the United States, in the Arctic region seriously.”</span></p><p data-end="1955" data-start="1620"><span class="css-1jxf684 r-bcqeeo r-1ttztb7 r-qvutc0 r-poiln3">“In that context, responding with tariffs would be highly illogical,” Boswijk said.</span></p><h2 data-end="1955" data-start="1620">Exports</h2><p data-end="2259" data-start="1957">Dutch businesses also warned of serious economic damage if the tariffs go ahead. Exporters’ association <a href="https://www.transport-online.nl/114298/evofenedex-heffingen-slecht-voor-handelsrelatie-met-vs/">Evofenedex</a> said the tariffs are “very harmful” for companies trading with the US, creating uncertainty over whether to continue exporting or look for alternative markets.</p><p data-end="2593" data-start="2261">In 2024, the Netherlands exported more than €38 billion worth of goods to the US, nearly 6% of total exports, while imports from the US totalled almost €60 billion.</p><p data-end="3029" data-start="2595">Within Europe, criticism was outspoken. Swedish prime minister <span class="hover:entity-accent entity-underline inline cursor-pointer align-baseline"><span class="whitespace-normal">Ulf Kristersson</span></span> said Europe “will not be blackmailed”, while French president <span class="hover:entity-accent entity-underline inline cursor-pointer align-baseline"><span class="whitespace-normal">Emmanuel Macron</span></span> called the tariffs “unacceptable” and said no intimidation would influence France.</p><p data-end="3029" data-start="2595">British prime minister <span class="hover:entity-accent entity-underline inline cursor-pointer align-baseline"><span class="whitespace-normal">Keir Starmer</span></span> said imposing tariffs on allies pursuing collective Nato security was “completely wrong”.</p><h2 data-end="3029" data-start="2595">Retaliation</h2><p data-end="3373" data-start="3031">Some have already called for the <span class="css-1jxf684 r-bcqeeo r-1ttztb7 r-qvutc0 r-poiln3">recently agreed EU–US. trade deal to be put on hold because of the US threat.</span></p><p data-end="3373" data-start="3031">Dutch MEP <span class="hover:entity-accent entity-underline inline cursor-pointer align-baseline"><span class="whitespace-normal">Bart Groothuis</span></span> said the EU should be prepared to respond more forcefully, including by deploying the bloc’s anti-coercion instrument, which could target US companies through trade restrictions, public procurement bans or limits on intellectual property rights. “At some point we have to draw a line,” he said.</p><p data-end="3684" data-start="3375">The commander of the Dutch armed forces <span class="hover:entity-accent entity-underline inline cursor-pointer align-baseline"><span class="whitespace-normal">Onno Eichelsheim</span></span> warned that escalating tensions risk creating a rift within Nato. “That plays into Putin’s hands,” he told Nieuwsuur on Saturday.</p><p data-end="3889" data-is-last-node="" data-is-only-node="" data-start="3686">EU member states are due to discuss the US tariffs collectively on Sunday afternoon.</p></main><div class="ad-container overflow-hidden d-none d-md-block p-4 bg-light mt-8 mb-10 mx-lg-4"><div class="bg-light p-lg-2 h-100 w-100 d-flex align-items-center justify-content-center position-relative" data-tagname="ROS_Native"><div id="div-gpt-ad-dutchnews_ros_native" style="display:block;"></div></div></div><div class="ad-container overflow-hidden d-block d-md-none bg-light my-8"><div class="bg-light p-lg-2 h-100 w-100 d-flex align-items-center justify-content-center position-relative" data-tagname="ROS_Native"><div id="div-gpt-ad-dutchnews_ros_native-m" style="display:block;"></div></div></div><footer class="my-8 px-4"><div class="pb-8"></div> <a class="btn btn-secondary btn-sm" href="/category/dutch-european-news/?list"></a> <a class="btn btn-secondary btn-sm" href="/category/foreign-affairs/?list"></a> <a class="btn btn-secondary btn-sm" href="/category/greenland/?list"></a> <a class="btn btn-secondary btn-sm" href="/category/nato/?list"></a> <a class="btn btn-secondary btn-sm" href="/category/us/?list"></a></footer><div class="bg-green-light p-3 mx-4 mt-8 mb-12"></div></article>]]></description><guid>https://www.dutchnews.nl/?p=262354</guid><pubDate>Sun, 18 Jan 2026 09:12:07 -0000</pubDate><dc:creator><![CDATA[Robin Pascoe]]></dc:creator></item><item><title>Mayors slam New Year firework clubs plan as risky, unworkable</title><link>https://www.dutchnews.nl/2026/01/mayors-slam-new-year-firework-clubs-plan-as-risky-unworkable/</link><description><![CDATA[<article class="post-262349 post type-post status-publish format-standard has-post-thumbnail hentry category-accidents category-fireworks category-society"><header class="pb-4 px-4"><h1 class="text-serif lh-1"> Mayors slam New Year firework clubs plan as risky, unworkable</h1> <time class="text-secondary updated me-2" datetime="2026-01-17T18:12:14+00:00"> January 17, 2026 </time></header><figure aria-describedby="caption-attachment-107150" class="px-lg-5" id="attachment_107150"> <img alt="" class="attachment-full size-full wp-post-image" decoding="async" fetchpriority="high" height="702" sizes="(max-width: 1000px) 100vw, 1000px" src="/wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2017/06/New-Year-fireworks-in-Amsterdam.jpg" srcset="/wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2017/06/New-Year-fireworks-in-Amsterdam.jpg 1000w, /wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2017/06/New-Year-fireworks-in-Amsterdam-560x393.jpg 560w, /wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2017/06/New-Year-fireworks-in-Amsterdam-768x539.jpg 768w, /wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2017/06/New-Year-fireworks-in-Amsterdam-300x211.jpg 300w" width="1000"/><figcaption class="px-4 px-lg-0" id="caption-attachment-107150"> New Year fireworks in Amsterdam. Photo: Depositphotos.com</figcaption></figure><main class="px-4"><p data-end="312" data-start="116">The mayors of several large Dutch cities have slammed the outgoing government’s decision to allow people to set up “<a href="https://www.dutchnews.nl/2026/01/ministers-back-licenced-neighbourhood-new-year-firework-clubs/">firework clubs</a>” to organise fireworks displays during the New Year celebrations.</p><p data-end="439" data-start="314">They say the plan is unworkable and risks undermining the nationwide ban on consumer firework sales which is due to come into effect at the end of this year.</p><p data-end="637" data-start="441">The plan envisages mayors granting licences to neighbourhoo clubs that will have to be registered with the chamber of trade. Those responsible for setting off fireworks will also have to take an online course.</p><p data-end="637" data-start="441"><div class="ad-container overflow-hidden p-4 bg-light my-8 d-none d-md-block"><div class="bg-light p-lg-2 h-100 w-100 d-flex align-items-center justify-content-center position-relative" data-tagname="ROS_Inarticle"><div id="div-gpt-ad-dutchnews_ros_inarticle" style="display:block;"></div></div></div><div class="ad-container overflow-hidden p-4 bg-light my-8 d-block d-md-none"><div class="bg-light p-lg-2 h-100 w-100 d-flex align-items-center justify-content-center position-relative" data-tagname="ROS_Inarticle"><div id="div-gpt-ad-dutchnews_ros_inarticle-m" style="display:block;"></div></div></div></p><p data-end="637" data-start="441">Local authorities will be able to introduce their own additional rules taking local circumstances into account. But Nijmegen mayor Hubert Bruls, who chairs the national safety board association, said staff shortages are already acute on New Year’s Eve, even without organised events.</p><p data-end="989" data-start="639">“I need every police officer, firefighter and ambulance crew I have just to keep things under control,” he said. “I simply do not have the capacity to supervise organised fireworks.”</p><p data-end="1088" data-start="991">Allowing firework clubs, the mayors say, risks recreating the very chaos the ban is meant to prevent.</p><p data-end="1088" data-start="991"><div class="ad-container overflow-hidden p-4 bg-light my-8 d-none d-md-block"><div class="bg-light p-lg-2 h-100 w-100 d-flex align-items-center justify-content-center position-relative" data-tagname="ROS_Incontent"><div id="div-gpt-ad-dutchnews_ros_incontent" style="display:block;"></div></div></div><div class="ad-container overflow-hidden p-4 bg-light my-8 d-block d-md-none"><div class="bg-light p-lg-2 h-100 w-100 d-flex align-items-center justify-content-center position-relative" data-tagname="ROS_Incontent"><div id="div-gpt-ad-dutchnews_ros_incontent-m" style="display:block;"></div></div></div></p><p data-end="1480" data-is-last-node="" data-is-only-node="" data-start="1218">Bruls said he hopes the government presses ahead with a straightforward nationwide ban for the coming New Year. “Perhaps it sounds cynical,” he said, “but after the violence of the last New Year’s Eve, even people who were against a ban now see the need for it.”</p><p>The emergency services, local councils and some national politicians have long campaigned for an end to the sale of fireworks to consumers, apart from the very lightest type.</p><p>Every year the New Year is celebrated in the Netherlands in a firework frenzy resulting in lost limbs and eyes and millions of damage to private property.</p></main><div class="ad-container overflow-hidden d-none d-md-block p-4 bg-light mt-8 mb-10 mx-lg-4"><div class="bg-light p-lg-2 h-100 w-100 d-flex align-items-center justify-content-center position-relative" data-tagname="ROS_Native"><div id="div-gpt-ad-dutchnews_ros_native" style="display:block;"></div></div></div><div class="ad-container overflow-hidden d-block d-md-none bg-light my-8"><div class="bg-light p-lg-2 h-100 w-100 d-flex align-items-center justify-content-center position-relative" data-tagname="ROS_Native"><div id="div-gpt-ad-dutchnews_ros_native-m" style="display:block;"></div></div></div><footer class="my-8 px-4"><div class="pb-8"></div> <a class="btn btn-secondary btn-sm" href="/category/accidents/?list"></a> <a class="btn btn-secondary btn-sm" href="/category/fireworks/?list"></a> <a class="btn btn-secondary btn-sm" href="/category/society/?list"></a></footer><div class="bg-green-light p-3 mx-4 mt-8 mb-12"></div></article>]]></description><guid>https://www.dutchnews.nl/?p=262349</guid><pubDate>Sat, 17 Jan 2026 18:12:14 -0000</pubDate><dc:creator><![CDATA[Robin Pascoe]]></dc:creator></item><item><title>Former D66 leader Sigrid Kaag on Trump’s Gaza peace team</title><link>https://www.dutchnews.nl/2026/01/former-d66-leader-sigrid-kaag-on-trumps-gaza-peace-team/</link><description><![CDATA[<article class="post-262345 post type-post status-publish format-standard has-post-thumbnail hentry category-foreign-affairs category-gaza category-middle-east category-us"><header class="pb-4 px-4"><h1 class="text-serif lh-1"> Former D66 leader Sigrid Kaag on Trump’s Gaza peace team</h1> <time class="text-secondary updated me-2" datetime="2026-01-17T17:57:10+00:00"> January 17, 2026 </time></header><figure aria-describedby="caption-attachment-262346" class="px-lg-5" id="attachment_262346"> <img alt="" class="attachment-full size-full wp-post-image" decoding="async" fetchpriority="high" height="667" sizes="(max-width: 1000px) 100vw, 1000px" src="/wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/ANP-534709897.jpg" srcset="/wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/ANP-534709897.jpg 1000w, /wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/ANP-534709897-560x374.jpg 560w, /wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/ANP-534709897-360x240.jpg 360w, /wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/ANP-534709897-768x512.jpg 768w" width="1000"/><figcaption class="px-4 px-lg-0" id="caption-attachment-262346"> Sigrid Kaag speaking to students last September. Photo: Ramon van Flymen ANP</figcaption></figure><main class="px-4"><p>Sigrid Kaag, the former D66 leader and finance minister, is listed as one of 11 Donald Trump appointees to a new<strong> “</strong>Gaza Executive Board” to help deliver “peace, stability, and prosperity for the people of Gaza”.</p><p>The Gaza board is a separate entity to Trump’s “board of peace” which includes US secretary of state, Marco Rubio, and former British prime minister Tony Blair, as well as property developer Steve Witkoff, and the president’s son-in-law Jared Kushner.</p><p>However, Blair, Witkoff and Kushner are also part of the board featuring Kaag, who became the United Nations envoy for the reconstruction of Gaza after leaving national politics and went on to become the UN’s envoy for the Middle East peace process.</p><div class="ad-container overflow-hidden p-4 bg-light my-8 d-none d-md-block"><div class="bg-light p-lg-2 h-100 w-100 d-flex align-items-center justify-content-center position-relative" data-tagname="ROS_Inarticle"><div id="div-gpt-ad-dutchnews_ros_inarticle" style="display:block;"></div></div></div><div class="ad-container overflow-hidden p-4 bg-light my-8 d-block d-md-none"><div class="bg-light p-lg-2 h-100 w-100 d-flex align-items-center justify-content-center position-relative" data-tagname="ROS_Inarticle"><div id="div-gpt-ad-dutchnews_ros_inarticle-m" style="display:block;"></div></div></div><p>“The United States remains fully committed to supporting this transitional framework, working in close partnership with Israel, key Arab nations, and the international community to achieve the objectives of the Comprehensive Plan,” the <a href="https://www.whitehouse.gov/briefings-statements/2026/01/statement-on-president-trumps-comprehensive-plan-to-end-the-gaza-conflict/">White House statement</a> said.</p><p>Additional executive board and Gaza executive board members will be announced over the coming weeks.</p><p>Kaag is one of two women on Trump’s newly announced team.</p><div class="ad-container overflow-hidden p-4 bg-light my-8 d-none d-md-block"><div class="bg-light p-lg-2 h-100 w-100 d-flex align-items-center justify-content-center position-relative" data-tagname="ROS_Incontent"><div id="div-gpt-ad-dutchnews_ros_incontent" style="display:block;"></div></div></div><div class="ad-container overflow-hidden p-4 bg-light my-8 d-block d-md-none"><div class="bg-light p-lg-2 h-100 w-100 d-flex align-items-center justify-content-center position-relative" data-tagname="ROS_Incontent"><div id="div-gpt-ad-dutchnews_ros_incontent-m" style="display:block;"></div></div></div><p>Kaag stepped down from her UN role last June, saying the post should be reshaped or even abolished.</p><p>She said at the time the peace process was on “on life support” and said she had initially accepted the post out of a sense of duty, after a direct request from then-US Secretary of State Antony Blinken.</p><p>Kaag has spent most of her career at the UN, first joining the organisation in 1994. She previously held the role of special coordinator for the Organisation for the Prohibition of Chemical Weapons mission in Syria and special coordinator of the United Nations in Lebanon.</p><p>She has not yet commented on the White House statement.</p></main><div class="ad-container overflow-hidden d-none d-md-block p-4 bg-light mt-8 mb-10 mx-lg-4"><div class="bg-light p-lg-2 h-100 w-100 d-flex align-items-center justify-content-center position-relative" data-tagname="ROS_Native"><div id="div-gpt-ad-dutchnews_ros_native" style="display:block;"></div></div></div><div class="ad-container overflow-hidden d-block d-md-none bg-light my-8"><div class="bg-light p-lg-2 h-100 w-100 d-flex align-items-center justify-content-center position-relative" data-tagname="ROS_Native"><div id="div-gpt-ad-dutchnews_ros_native-m" style="display:block;"></div></div></div><footer class="my-8 px-4"><div class="pb-8"></div> <a class="btn btn-secondary btn-sm" href="/category/foreign-affairs/?list"></a> <a class="btn btn-secondary btn-sm" href="/category/gaza/?list"></a> <a class="btn btn-secondary btn-sm" href="/category/middle-east/?list"></a> <a class="btn btn-secondary btn-sm" href="/category/us/?list"></a></footer><div class="bg-green-light p-3 mx-4 mt-8 mb-12"></div></article>]]></description><guid>https://www.dutchnews.nl/?p=262345</guid><pubDate>Sat, 17 Jan 2026 17:57:10 -0000</pubDate><dc:creator><![CDATA[Robin Pascoe]]></dc:creator></item><item><title>NL among countries hit by Trump tariffs for supporting Greenland</title><link>https://www.dutchnews.nl/2026/01/nl-among-countries-hit-by-trump-tariffs-for-support-of-greenland/</link><description><![CDATA[<article class="post-262336 post type-post status-publish format-standard has-post-thumbnail hentry category-greenland category-tariffs category-united-states category-us"><header class="pb-4 px-4"><h1 class="text-serif lh-1"> NL among countries hit by Trump tariffs for supporting Greenland</h1> <time class="text-secondary updated me-2" datetime="2026-01-17T17:33:21+00:00"> January 17, 2026 </time></header><figure aria-describedby="caption-attachment-262187" class="px-lg-5" id="attachment_262187"> <img alt="" class="attachment-full size-full wp-post-image" decoding="async" fetchpriority="high" height="1333" sizes="(max-width: 2000px) 100vw, 2000px" src="/wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/Depositphotos_95515150_L.jpg" srcset="/wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/Depositphotos_95515150_L.jpg 2000w, /wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/Depositphotos_95515150_L-560x373.jpg 560w, /wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/Depositphotos_95515150_L-1200x800.jpg 1200w, /wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/Depositphotos_95515150_L-360x240.jpg 360w, /wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/Depositphotos_95515150_L-768x512.jpg 768w, /wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/Depositphotos_95515150_L-1536x1024.jpg 1536w" width="2000"/><figcaption class="px-4 px-lg-0" id="caption-attachment-262187"> Photo: Depositphotos</figcaption></figure><main class="px-4"><p>US President Trump announced in a post on social media on Saturday that he will impose a 10% tariff on all goods coming from the Netherlands and seven other European countries for their support of Greenland.</p><p>Earlier this week, the Netherlands announced is sending two members of the armed forces to the Arctic Island as part of preparations for Nato exercises.</p><p>Trump has stepped up calls in the past two weeks to take over Greenland, which is an autonomous territory within the Danish kingdom.</p><div class="ad-container overflow-hidden p-4 bg-light my-8 d-none d-md-block"><div class="bg-light p-lg-2 h-100 w-100 d-flex align-items-center justify-content-center position-relative" data-tagname="ROS_Inarticle"><div id="div-gpt-ad-dutchnews_ros_inarticle" style="display:block;"></div></div></div><div class="ad-container overflow-hidden p-4 bg-light my-8 d-block d-md-none"><div class="bg-light p-lg-2 h-100 w-100 d-flex align-items-center justify-content-center position-relative" data-tagname="ROS_Inarticle"><div id="div-gpt-ad-dutchnews_ros_inarticle-m" style="display:block;"></div></div></div><p>“Denmark, Norway, Sweden, France, Germany, the United Kingdom, the Netherlands, and Finland have journeyed to Greenland, for purposes unknown. This is a very dangerous situation for the Safety, Security, and Survival of our Planet,” Trump said in a lengthy post on the website Truth Social.</p><p>The rate will come into effect on February 1 and rise to 25% in June if a deal is not reached for the “Complete and Total purchase of Greenland,” according to Trump’s post.</p><p>All eight countries have said they will send military personnel to Greenland in recent days.</p><div class="ad-container overflow-hidden p-4 bg-light my-8 d-none d-md-block"><div class="bg-light p-lg-2 h-100 w-100 d-flex align-items-center justify-content-center position-relative" data-tagname="ROS_Incontent"><div id="div-gpt-ad-dutchnews_ros_incontent" style="display:block;"></div></div></div><div class="ad-container overflow-hidden p-4 bg-light my-8 d-block d-md-none"><div class="bg-light p-lg-2 h-100 w-100 d-flex align-items-center justify-content-center position-relative" data-tagname="ROS_Incontent"><div id="div-gpt-ad-dutchnews_ros_incontent-m" style="display:block;"></div></div></div><p>The countries are preparing for a military exercise in Greenland, led by Denmark. Dutch foreign minister Ruben Brekelmans said in a statement this week that a larger Nato deployment could be possible.</p><h2>Dutch reaction</h2><p>Foreign minister David van Weel said on Saturday evening that the Netherlands had “taken note” of Trump’s tariff announcement.</p><p>“<span class="css-1jxf684 r-bcqeeo r-1ttztb7 r-qvutc0 r-poiln3">Military efforts related to exercises in Greenland are intended to contribute to security in the Arctic region,” he said on social media. “The Netherlands is in close contact with the European Commission </span><span class="css-1jxf684 r-bcqeeo r-1ttztb7 r-qvutc0 r-poiln3">and partners on our response.”</span></p><p>The German government also published a similar holding statement, adding that “<span class="css-1jxf684 r-bcqeeo r-1ttztb7 r-qvutc0 r-poiln3">together we will decide on appropriate responses at the appropriate time.”</span></p></main><div class="ad-container overflow-hidden d-none d-md-block p-4 bg-light mt-8 mb-10 mx-lg-4"><div class="bg-light p-lg-2 h-100 w-100 d-flex align-items-center justify-content-center position-relative" data-tagname="ROS_Native"><div id="div-gpt-ad-dutchnews_ros_native" style="display:block;"></div></div></div><div class="ad-container overflow-hidden d-block d-md-none bg-light my-8"><div class="bg-light p-lg-2 h-100 w-100 d-flex align-items-center justify-content-center position-relative" data-tagname="ROS_Native"><div id="div-gpt-ad-dutchnews_ros_native-m" style="display:block;"></div></div></div><footer class="my-8 px-4"><div class="pb-8"></div> <a class="btn btn-secondary btn-sm" href="/category/greenland/?list"></a> <a class="btn btn-secondary btn-sm" href="/category/tariffs/?list"></a> <a class="btn btn-secondary btn-sm" href="/category/united-states/?list"></a> <a class="btn btn-secondary btn-sm" href="/category/us/?list"></a></footer><div class="bg-green-light p-3 mx-4 mt-8 mb-12"></div></article>]]></description><guid>https://www.dutchnews.nl/?p=262336</guid><pubDate>Sat, 17 Jan 2026 17:33:21 -0000</pubDate><dc:creator><![CDATA[Molly Quell]]></dc:creator></item><item><title>Dutch seize three tonnes of cannabis sweets and honey from US</title><link>https://www.dutchnews.nl/2026/01/dutch-seize-three-tonnes-of-cannabis-sweets-and-honey-from-us/</link><description><![CDATA[<article class="post-262337 post type-post status-publish format-standard has-post-thumbnail hentry category-cannabis category-drugs category-schiphol"><header class="pb-4 px-4"><h1 class="text-serif lh-1"> Dutch seize three tonnes of cannabis sweets and honey from US</h1> <time class="text-secondary updated me-2" datetime="2026-01-17T17:14:16+00:00"> January 17, 2026 </time></header><figure aria-describedby="caption-attachment-262338" class="px-lg-5" id="attachment_262338"> <img alt="" class="attachment-full size-full wp-post-image" decoding="async" fetchpriority="high" height="373" sizes="(max-width: 593px) 100vw, 593px" src="/wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/winegums1-e1768669936925.jpeg" srcset="/wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/winegums1-e1768669936925.jpeg 593w, /wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/winegums1-e1768669936925-560x352.jpeg 560w" width="593"/><figcaption class="px-4 px-lg-0" id="caption-attachment-262338"> Part of the haul. Photo: Douane</figcaption></figure><main class="px-4"><p data-end="153" data-start="0">Dutch customs officers have intercepted more than three tonnes of sweets and honey containing THC, psychoactive substance found in cannabis, during checks at <span class="hover:entity-accent entity-underline inline cursor-pointer align-baseline"><span class="whitespace-normal">Schiphol</span></span> airport.</p><p data-end="339" data-start="155">The two consignments, with a combined weight of around 3,220 kilos, consisted of wine gums and jars of honey. The goods were discovered this week after sniffer dogs inspected several shipments arriving from the United States and destined for the Dutch and Czech markets.</p><p data-end="903" data-start="706">Further testing showed the products contained tetrahydrocannabinol, better known as THC. The substance is found in cannabis and hashish but is also used in edible products such as cakes and sweets.</p><p data-end="903" data-start="706"><div class="ad-container overflow-hidden p-4 bg-light my-8 d-none d-md-block"><div class="bg-light p-lg-2 h-100 w-100 d-flex align-items-center justify-content-center position-relative" data-tagname="ROS_Inarticle"><div id="div-gpt-ad-dutchnews_ros_inarticle" style="display:block;"></div></div></div><div class="ad-container overflow-hidden p-4 bg-light my-8 d-block d-md-none"><div class="bg-light p-lg-2 h-100 w-100 d-flex align-items-center justify-content-center position-relative" data-tagname="ROS_Inarticle"><div id="div-gpt-ad-dutchnews_ros_inarticle-m" style="display:block;"></div></div></div></p><p data-end="1380" data-start="1174">Although cannabis and hashish are classed as soft drugs in the Netherlands, THC itself is illegal. It is listed as a hard drug under the Opium Act, meaning it is illegal to produce, sell, buy or possess it.</p><p data-end="1504" data-is-last-node="" data-is-only-node="" data-start="1382">No arrests have been made in connection with the find, broadcaster NH Nieuws reported. The seized goods will be destroyed.</p></main><div class="ad-container overflow-hidden d-none d-md-block p-4 bg-light mt-8 mb-10 mx-lg-4"><div class="bg-light p-lg-2 h-100 w-100 d-flex align-items-center justify-content-center position-relative" data-tagname="ROS_Native"><div id="div-gpt-ad-dutchnews_ros_native" style="display:block;"></div></div></div><div class="ad-container overflow-hidden d-block d-md-none bg-light my-8"><div class="bg-light p-lg-2 h-100 w-100 d-flex align-items-center justify-content-center position-relative" data-tagname="ROS_Native"><div id="div-gpt-ad-dutchnews_ros_native-m" style="display:block;"></div></div></div><footer class="my-8 px-4"><div class="pb-8"></div> <a class="btn btn-secondary btn-sm" href="/category/cannabis/?list"></a> <a class="btn btn-secondary btn-sm" href="/category/drugs/?list"></a> <a class="btn btn-secondary btn-sm" href="/category/amsterdam/schiphol/?list"></a></footer><div class="bg-green-light p-3 mx-4 mt-8 mb-12"></div></article>]]></description><guid>https://www.dutchnews.nl/?p=262337</guid><pubDate>Sat, 17 Jan 2026 17:14:16 -0000</pubDate><dc:creator><![CDATA[Robin Pascoe]]></dc:creator></item><item><title>Podcast: The Cock and Bull and Wood Edition</title><link>https://www.dutchnews.nl/2026/01/podcast-the-cock-and-bull-and-wood-edition/</link><description><![CDATA[<article class="post-262309 post type-post status-publish format-standard has-post-thumbnail hentry category-uncategorized type-podcast newsletter-include"><header class="pb-4 px-4"><h1 class="text-serif lh-1"> Podcast: The Cock and Bull and Wood Edition</h1> <time class="text-secondary updated me-2" datetime="2026-01-16T13:12:57+00:00"> January 16, 2026 </time></header><figure aria-describedby="caption-attachment-262314" class="px-lg-5" id="attachment_262314"> <img alt="" class="attachment-full size-full wp-post-image" decoding="async" fetchpriority="high" height="1334" sizes="(max-width: 1868px) 100vw, 1868px" src="/wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/De-Stier-Goldenballs.jpg" srcset="/wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/De-Stier-Goldenballs.jpg 1868w, /wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/De-Stier-Goldenballs-560x400.jpg 560w, /wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/De-Stier-Goldenballs-1200x857.jpg 1200w, /wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/De-Stier-Goldenballs-768x548.jpg 768w, /wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/De-Stier-Goldenballs-1536x1097.jpg 1536w" width="1868"/><figcaption class="px-4 px-lg-0" id="caption-attachment-262314"> It wasn't called the Golden Age for nothing (With apologies to Paulus Potter)</figcaption></figure><main class="px-4"><p><a href="https://www.patreon.com/DutchNewsNL"><strong>Want to support the DutchNews podcast and keep up our stocks of stroopwafels and orange tompouces? Click here to become a Patreon backer</strong></a></p><p>The new coalition leaders signal a break from unstable political experiments by forming a minority government that depends on the support of parties they turned down as partners. Greenland breathes a sigh of relief as the Dutch dispatch a lone naval officer to defend it against the US army. Contrasting fortunes in Amsterdam as the AEX soars past 1,000 points while Ajax crash to their worst cup defeat in 99 years. And art experts find two huge Easter eggs concealed in one of the Mauritshuis’s best known paintings.</p><p><iframe frameborder="no" height="300" scrolling="no" src="https://w.soundcloud.com/player/?url=https%3A//api.soundcloud.com/tracks/soundcloud%253Atracks%253A2248551140&amp;color=%23ff5500&amp;auto_play=false&amp;hide_related=false&amp;show_comments=true&amp;show_user=true&amp;show_reposts=false&amp;show_teaser=true&amp;visual=true" width="100%"></iframe></p><div style="font-size: 10px; color: #cccccc; line-break: anywhere; word-break: normal; overflow: hidden; white-space: nowrap; text-overflow: ellipsis; font-family: Interstate,Lucida Grande,Lucida Sans Unicode,Lucida Sans,Garuda,Verdana,Tahoma,sans-serif; font-weight: 100;"><a href="https://soundcloud.com/dutchnewsnl" rel="noopener" style="color: #cccccc; text-decoration: none;" target="_blank" title="Dutch News">Dutch News</a> · <a href="https://soundcloud.com/dutchnewsnl/the-cock-and-bull-and-wood-edition-week-3-2026" rel="noopener" style="color: #cccccc; text-decoration: none;" target="_blank" title="The Cock and Bull and Wood Edition - Week 3 - 2026">The Cock and Bull and Wood Edition – Week 3 – 2026</a></div><p><strong>Ophef of the week:</strong> <a href="https://www.bnnvara.nl/joop/artikelen/niet-bepaald-wakker-en-vrij-in-paraguay">Broadcaster under fire for showcasing conspiracy theorists’ expat commune</a> (BNNVara)</p><p><a href="https://www.rtl.nl/nieuws/binnenland/artikel/5553885/ruinen-drenthe-wolf-basisschool-dicht-overdreven">Wolf experts slam Drenthe primary school closure as overreaction</a> (RTL)</p><p><a href="https://nos.nl/artikel/2598202-geliefde-stationskat-heeft-permanent-eerbetoon-bij-station-purmerend">Commuters erect statue to much missed railway station “house cat”</a> (NOS)</p><p><strong>News</strong></p><p><a href="https://www.dutchnews.nl/2026/01/february-23-pencilled-in-as-cabinet-deadline-as-talks-continue/">February 23 pencilled in as deadline to form new government as talks continue</a></p><p><a href="https://www.dutchnews.nl/2026/01/curacao-hopes-to-become-a-key-caribbean-hub-for-venezuelan-oil/">Curaçao could become key hub for Venezuelan oil following US intevention</a></p><p><a href="https://www.dutchnews.nl/2026/01/dutch-summon-iranian-ambassador-over-bloody-repression/">Dutch summon Iranian ambassador over bloody crackdown on street protests</a></p><p><a href="https://www.dutchnews.nl/2026/01/dutch-to-decide-this-week-about-sending-troops-to-greenland/">Netherlands decides to send one naval officer to join Greenland mission</a></p><p><a href="https://www.dutchnews.nl/2026/01/amsterdam-stock-exchange-breaks-1000-points-in-new-record/">Amsterdam stock exchange surges through 1,000-point barrier</a></p><p><a href="https://www.dutchnews.nl/2026/01/rents-beef-and-coffee-behind-high-dutch-inflation-in-2025/">Rents, beef and coffee stoke inflation as headline rate stays at 3.3%</a></p><p><a href="https://www.dutchnews.nl/2026/01/fewer-firms-go-bust-as-bankruptcy-rate-goes-down-15/">Fewer firms go bust, bankruptcy rate down by 15% in 2025</a></p><p><a href="https://www.dutchnews.nl/2026/01/experts-want-insight-into-takeover-of-digid-platform-by-us-firm/">Experts concerned about takeover of DigiD platform by US company</a></p><p><a href="https://www.dutchnews.nl/2026/01/not-a-load-of-bull-classic-painting-once-showed-larger-genitals/">Not a load of bull: Classic painting once featured more prominent genitals</a></p><p><strong>Sport</strong></p><p><a href="https://www.dutchnews.nl/2026/01/az-hammer-ajax-6-0-in-knvb-cup-psv-beat-den-bosch/">AZ hammer Ajax 6-0 in Dutch cup, PSV cruise past Den Bosch</a></p><p><a href="https://www.dutchnews.nl/2026/01/cricket-klaassen-van-beek-return-to-squad-for-t20-world-cup/">Klaassen and Van Beek recalled to Netherlands squad for T20 World Cup</a></p><p> </p></main><div class="ad-container overflow-hidden d-none d-md-block p-4 bg-light mt-8 mb-10 mx-lg-4"><div class="bg-light p-lg-2 h-100 w-100 d-flex align-items-center justify-content-center position-relative" data-tagname="ROS_Native"><div id="div-gpt-ad-dutchnews_ros_native" style="display:block;"></div></div></div><div class="ad-container overflow-hidden d-block d-md-none bg-light my-8"><div class="bg-light p-lg-2 h-100 w-100 d-flex align-items-center justify-content-center position-relative" data-tagname="ROS_Native"><div id="div-gpt-ad-dutchnews_ros_native-m" style="display:block;"></div></div></div><footer class="my-8 px-4"><div class="pb-8"></div> <a class="btn btn-primary btn-sm" href="/life-in-the-netherlands/podcast/"></a> <a class="btn btn-secondary btn-sm" href="/category/uncategorized/?list"></a></footer><div class="bg-green-light p-3 mx-4 mt-8 mb-12"></div></article>]]></description><guid>https://www.dutchnews.nl/?p=262309</guid><pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 13:12:57 -0000</pubDate><dc:creator><![CDATA[Gordon Darroch]]></dc:creator></item><item><title>Ministers back licenced neighbourhood New Year firework clubs</title><link>https://www.dutchnews.nl/2026/01/ministers-back-licenced-neighbourhood-new-year-firework-clubs/</link><description><![CDATA[<article class="post-262331 post type-post status-publish format-standard has-post-thumbnail hentry category-accidents category-fireworks category-new-year category-society newsletter-top-article"><header class="pb-4 px-4"><h1 class="text-serif lh-1"> Ministers back licenced neighbourhood New Year firework clubs</h1> <time class="text-secondary updated me-2" datetime="2026-01-16T12:43:02+00:00"> January 16, 2026 </time></header><figure aria-describedby="caption-attachment-207794" class="px-lg-5" id="attachment_207794"> <img alt="" class="attachment-full size-full wp-post-image" decoding="async" fetchpriority="high" height="667" sizes="(max-width: 1000px) 100vw, 1000px" src="/wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/Depositphotos_497426438_S.jpg" srcset="/wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/Depositphotos_497426438_S.jpg 1000w, /wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/Depositphotos_497426438_S-560x374.jpg 560w, /wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/Depositphotos_497426438_S-360x240.jpg 360w, /wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/Depositphotos_497426438_S-768x512.jpg 768w, /wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/Depositphotos_497426438_S-640x427.jpg 640w, /wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/Depositphotos_497426438_S-92x62.jpg 92w, /wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/Depositphotos_497426438_S-130x87.jpg 130w" width="1000"/><figcaption class="px-4 px-lg-0" id="caption-attachment-207794"> Photo: Depositphotos.com</figcaption></figure><main class="px-4"><p data-end="307" data-start="116">Local authorities will be able to license special “firework clubs” to set up New Year displays when the ban on consumer fireworks comes into force this year, the outgoing cabinet has decided.</p><p data-end="586" data-start="309">The associations will have to meet a number of strict conditions and it will be up to local mayors how many permits they hand out. The associations must also be registered with the chamber of trade and will face a limit of 200 kilos of fireworks that fall into the F2 category.</p><p data-end="867" data-start="588">The public will have to keep a minimum distance from the fireworks, and those setting them off should not have been taking drugs or drinking alcohol. They must also take an online course in firework safety, which junior minister Thierry Aartsen described as “low threshold”.</p><p data-end="867" data-start="588"><div class="ad-container overflow-hidden p-4 bg-light my-8 d-none d-md-block"><div class="bg-light p-lg-2 h-100 w-100 d-flex align-items-center justify-content-center position-relative" data-tagname="ROS_Inarticle"><div id="div-gpt-ad-dutchnews_ros_inarticle" style="display:block;"></div></div></div><div class="ad-container overflow-hidden p-4 bg-light my-8 d-block d-md-none"><div class="bg-light p-lg-2 h-100 w-100 d-flex align-items-center justify-content-center position-relative" data-tagname="ROS_Inarticle"><div id="div-gpt-ad-dutchnews_ros_inarticle-m" style="display:block;"></div></div></div></p><p data-end="1001" data-start="869">Local authorities will be able to introduce their own additional rules taking local circumstances into account.</p><p data-end="1191" data-start="1003">The cabinet expects the new rules will lead to fewer sales and is prepared to compensate sellers who lose their businesses as a result. The Netherlands has some 800 legal firework sellers and the rules for how they should be compensated are currently being worked out.</p><p data-end="1368" data-start="1193">The plan is based on draft legislation that was passed in both houses of parliament last year. The lower house and senate will have to vote again on the new regulations.</p><p data-end="1487" data-is-last-node="" data-is-only-node="" data-start="1370"><div class="ad-container overflow-hidden p-4 bg-light my-8 d-none d-md-block"><div class="bg-light p-lg-2 h-100 w-100 d-flex align-items-center justify-content-center position-relative" data-tagname="ROS_Incontent"><div id="div-gpt-ad-dutchnews_ros_incontent" style="display:block;"></div></div></div><div class="ad-container overflow-hidden p-4 bg-light my-8 d-block d-md-none"><div class="bg-light p-lg-2 h-100 w-100 d-flex align-items-center justify-content-center position-relative" data-tagname="ROS_Incontent"><div id="div-gpt-ad-dutchnews_ros_incontent-m" style="display:block;"></div></div></div></p><p>The emergency services, local councils and some national politicians have long campaigned for an end to the sale of fireworks to consumers, apart from the very lightest type.</p><p>Every year the New Year is celebrated in the Netherlands in a firework frenzy resulting in lost limbs and eyes and millions of damage to private property.</p><p>The Netherlands has also <a href="https://www.dutchnews.nl/2025/12/nl-calls-for-eu-ban-on-powerful-fireworks-as-explosions-continue/">called</a> for a Europe-wide ban on powerful fireworks, which are increasingly being used as explosives in gangland and private disputes.</p></main><div class="ad-container overflow-hidden d-none d-md-block p-4 bg-light mt-8 mb-10 mx-lg-4"><div class="bg-light p-lg-2 h-100 w-100 d-flex align-items-center justify-content-center position-relative" data-tagname="ROS_Native"><div id="div-gpt-ad-dutchnews_ros_native" style="display:block;"></div></div></div><div class="ad-container overflow-hidden d-block d-md-none bg-light my-8"><div class="bg-light p-lg-2 h-100 w-100 d-flex align-items-center justify-content-center position-relative" data-tagname="ROS_Native"><div id="div-gpt-ad-dutchnews_ros_native-m" style="display:block;"></div></div></div><footer class="my-8 px-4"><div class="pb-8"></div> <a class="btn btn-secondary btn-sm" href="/category/accidents/?list"></a> <a class="btn btn-secondary btn-sm" href="/category/fireworks/?list"></a> <a class="btn btn-secondary btn-sm" href="/category/new-year/?list"></a> <a class="btn btn-secondary btn-sm" href="/category/society/?list"></a></footer><div class="bg-green-light p-3 mx-4 mt-8 mb-12"></div></article>]]></description><guid>https://www.dutchnews.nl/?p=262331</guid><pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 12:43:02 -0000</pubDate><dc:creator><![CDATA[Robin Pascoe]]></dc:creator></item></channel></rss>