<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>DutchNews.nl</title><link>https://www.dutchnews.nl/</link><description>DutchNews.nl brings daily news from The Netherlands in English</description><lastBuildDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 09:48:42 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>New Margraten cemetery panels aim to quell Black Liberators row</title><link>https://www.dutchnews.nl/2026/01/new-margraten-cemetery-panels-aim-to-quell-black-liberators-row/</link><description><![CDATA[<article class="post-262750 post type-post status-publish format-standard has-post-thumbnail hentry category-margraten-cemetery category-society"><header class="pb-4 px-4"><h1 class="text-serif lh-1"> New Margraten cemetery panels aim to quell Black Liberators row</h1> <time class="text-secondary updated me-2" datetime="2026-01-27T09:25:06+00:00"> January 27, 2026 </time></header><figure aria-describedby="caption-attachment-262751" class="px-lg-5" id="attachment_262751"> <img alt="" class="attachment-full size-full wp-post-image" decoding="async" fetchpriority="high" height="2001" sizes="(max-width: 2560px) 100vw, 2560px" src="/wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/ANP-548659730-scaled.jpg" srcset="/wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/ANP-548659730-scaled.jpg 2560w, /wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/ANP-548659730-560x438.jpg 560w, /wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/ANP-548659730-1200x938.jpg 1200w, /wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/ANP-548659730-768x600.jpg 768w, /wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/ANP-548659730-1536x1201.jpg 1536w, /wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/ANP-548659730-2048x1601.jpg 2048w" width="2560"/><figcaption class="px-4 px-lg-0" id="caption-attachment-262751"> US ambassador Joe Popolo (l), author Robert M Edsel (c) and ABMC executive director Thomas Spoehr with the new panel. Photo: ANP/Remko de Waal</figcaption></figure><main class="px-4"><p>Ten new information panels have been unveiled for the American war cemetery in Margraten, including one focusing on the African-American soldiers who dug the original graves.</p><p>The other nine panels will be added to a rotating display featuring the stories of individual service members. They include two Black soldiers, one Native American and a woman who served as a nurse.</p><p>US ambassador Joe Popolo, who presented the panels at his official residence in The Hague on Monday, said the visitor centre displays were testament to the close relationship with the local population in Margraten who “have come forward and have taken over the maintenance of the graves.”</p><div class="ad-container overflow-hidden p-4 bg-light my-8 d-none d-md-block"><div class="bg-light p-lg-2 h-100 w-100 d-flex align-items-center justify-content-center position-relative" data-tagname="ROS_Inarticle"><div id="div-gpt-ad-dutchnews_ros_inarticle" style="display:block;"></div></div></div><div class="ad-container overflow-hidden p-4 bg-light my-8 d-block d-md-none"><div class="bg-light p-lg-2 h-100 w-100 d-flex align-items-center justify-content-center position-relative" data-tagname="ROS_Inarticle"><div id="div-gpt-ad-dutchnews_ros_inarticle-m" style="display:block;"></div></div></div><p>In November a row erupted over the removal of a previous panel describing how Black American soldiers faced discrimination in the segregated US army even as they fought to liberate Europe.</p><p>Relatives of soldiers buried at Margraten said the removal of the panels was <a href="https://www.dutchnews.nl/2025/11/relatives-outraged-at-removal-of-black-liberators-at-margraten/">“dishonouring” their memory</a> and accused the Trump administration of trying to erase them from history.</p><p>The mayor of Eijsden-Margraten, Alain Krijnen, <a href="https://www.dutchnews.nl/2025/11/mayor-calls-for-black-liberators-to-be-commemorated-at-margraten/">wrote to the ABMC</a> at the time asking for the story of the Black Liberators to be given “permanent attention in the visitor center”.</p><h2>“Whitewashed”</h2><p>The new panel details the units that created the first, temporary cemetery at Margraten, including the 611th Graves Registration Company and two Quartermaster Service Company units – segregated units that dug the graves – but without quotes or testimony from the service members themselves, or any mention of segregation.</p><p>Kees Ribbens, senior researcher at the Netherlands Institute for War, Holocaust, and Genocide Studies (NIOD), called it “unsettling and disappointing”. He told ANP: “The text of the new panel makes no mention whatsoever of segregation in the US Army. In that sense the image has been sanitised or whitewashed.”</p><p>Stichting Black Liberators, a Dutch foundation that commemorates the Black American soldiers who served in the Netherlands, said the panel was “a step in the right direction” but it would continue to work to highlight “a painful aspect of history for both the veterans themselves and their relatives who should never be forgotten.”</p><h2>Trump DEI order</h2><p>Referring to the criticism, Popolo said: “It kind of hurt inside that the very, very important work that this cemetery has done has been misconstrued in some respects and frankly hijacked away from the purpose.”</p><p>The previous panel was removed in March shortly after US president Donald Trump issued an executive order, titled Restoring Truth and Sanity to American History, calling for public monuments to be purged of the “corrosive ideology” that presented American history as “inherently racist, sexist, oppressive, or otherwise irredeemably flawed”.</p><div class="ad-container overflow-hidden p-4 bg-light my-8 d-none d-md-block"><div class="bg-light p-lg-2 h-100 w-100 d-flex align-items-center justify-content-center position-relative" data-tagname="ROS_Incontent"><div id="div-gpt-ad-dutchnews_ros_incontent" style="display:block;"></div></div></div><div class="ad-container overflow-hidden p-4 bg-light my-8 d-block d-md-none"><div class="bg-light p-lg-2 h-100 w-100 d-flex align-items-center justify-content-center position-relative" data-tagname="ROS_Incontent"><div id="div-gpt-ad-dutchnews_ros_incontent-m" style="display:block;"></div></div></div><p>The panel <a href="https://blackliberators.nl/stories/margraten">was titled “Fighting on Two Fronts”</a> and included a quote from staff sergeant Jefferson Wiggins, who was 19 at the time, describing how his comrades “cried when they were digging the graves … they were just completely traumatised.” It also described how segregation was abolished by President Truman after the war, in 1948.</p><p>The ABMC later said the panel would not be restored because it did not fit with its “commemorative mission”, despite calls from politicians in Limburg and relatives of fallen Black soldiers in the US to give ”permanent attention” to the story of the Black Liberators.</p><h2>Omissions</h2><p>At a press conference to unveil the new panel, the ABMC’s executive director, Thomas Spoehr, said the previous panel contained “omissions” that ”unintentionally excluded significant contributions to the temporary cemetery.”</p><p>Referring to the struggle against segregation, Spoehr said: “A visitor centre at the cemetery is not a general history museum. Our job in that visitor centre is to tell the stories of the soldiers and the sacrifices that they made.</p><p>“While racism and segregation is an important topic and one that needs to be talked about, it’s not part of the mission of the AMBC.”</p><p>Spoehr argued that the new panel was “more inclusive” because it referred to everyone involved in building the cemetery, including local Dutch citizens who helped out using tools from their farms.</p><h2>“Partial fix”</h2><p>Samuel de Korte, a Dutch writer specialising in Black American war history, described the new panel as a “partial fix” that failed to inform the public about the “core problem” of segregation and racism in the US Army.</p><p>”Black soldiers here fought a two‑front war: against Nazism and against Jim Crow,” he said. “As long as the story at Margraten omits that second front, the history remains incomplete and risks becoming a sanitized version that comforts us rather than tells the truth.”</p><p>As well as the gravediggers’ panel, nine panels have been added to the displays featuring the stories of individual service members, creating 24 in total that will be shown on rotation.</p><p>They include Private Richard Willoughby, from North Carolina, who was killed in action during the capture of the German town of Hann Münden, near Göttingen, on April 7, just before his 21st birthday.</p><p>Spoehr said Willoughby was one of more than 2,000 soldiers in segregated units who were drafted into the infantry during the campaign to liberate Europe in 1944.</p><h2>New faces</h2><p>Among the other new faces is Caswell Taylor, a private first class from Illinois, who was killed in a road collision a month before the liberation, while working on construction and water systems installations.</p><p>Private Jacob T. Herman Jr., native of the Ogala Sioux Tribe, was a 19-year-old paratrooper who died during Operation Market Garden, the failed attempt to liberate Arnhem in September 1944, while Christine A Gasvoda, one of four women buried at the cemetery, was a nurse who was killed in a plane crash during a resupply and evacuation mission.</p><p>Altogether 8,300 service members are buried at Margraten, including 172 Black Liberators, while another 1,700 names are inscribed on the Wall of the Missing. All of the graves are maintained by local Dutch citizens under an adoption scheme.</p><p>Last year the Monuments Men and Women Foundation launched its <a href="https://www.foreverpromise.org/">Forever Promise Project</a>, which aims to connect the Dutch adopters with the families of the service members they commemorate. The programme includes a website with a searchable database of all those buried at Margraten.</p><p>Its chairman, author Robert M. Edsel, told the press conference that some 400 American families had been linked to Dutch grave adopters since the project was launched five months ago.</p></main><div class="ad-container overflow-hidden d-none d-md-block p-4 bg-light mt-8 mb-10 mx-lg-4"><div class="bg-light p-lg-2 h-100 w-100 d-flex align-items-center justify-content-center position-relative" data-tagname="ROS_Native"><div id="div-gpt-ad-dutchnews_ros_native" style="display:block;"></div></div></div><div class="ad-container overflow-hidden d-block d-md-none bg-light my-8"><div class="bg-light p-lg-2 h-100 w-100 d-flex align-items-center justify-content-center position-relative" data-tagname="ROS_Native"><div id="div-gpt-ad-dutchnews_ros_native-m" style="display:block;"></div></div></div><footer class="my-8 px-4"><div class="pb-8"></div> <a class="btn btn-secondary btn-sm" href="/category/margraten-cemetery/?list"></a> <a class="btn btn-secondary btn-sm" href="/category/society/?list"></a></footer><div class="bg-green-light p-3 mx-4 mt-8 mb-12"></div></article>]]></description><guid>https://www.dutchnews.nl/?p=262750</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 09:25:06 -0000</pubDate><dc:creator><![CDATA[Gordon Darroch]]></dc:creator></item><item><title>Dutch public broadcasting system faces overhaul to cut costs</title><link>https://www.dutchnews.nl/2026/01/dutch-public-broadcasting-system-faces-overhaul-to-cut-costs/</link><description><![CDATA[<article class="post-262754 post type-post status-publish format-standard has-post-thumbnail hentry category-art-and-culture category-media category-society"><header class="pb-4 px-4"><h1 class="text-serif lh-1"> Dutch public broadcasting system faces overhaul to cut costs</h1> <time class="text-secondary updated me-2" datetime="2026-01-27T09:23:52+00:00"> January 27, 2026 </time></header><figure aria-describedby="caption-attachment-137851" class="px-lg-5" id="attachment_137851"> <img alt="" class="attachment-full size-full wp-post-image" decoding="async" fetchpriority="high" height="667" sizes="(max-width: 1000px) 100vw, 1000px" src="/wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2019/04/television-choice.jpg" srcset="/wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2019/04/television-choice.jpg 1000w, /wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2019/04/television-choice-360x240.jpg 360w, /wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2019/04/television-choice-560x374.jpg 560w, /wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2019/04/television-choice-768x512.jpg 768w, /wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2019/04/television-choice-640x427.jpg 640w, /wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2019/04/television-choice-100x67.jpg 100w, /wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2019/04/television-choice-130x87.jpg 130w" width="1000"/><figcaption class="px-4 px-lg-0" id="caption-attachment-137851"> Photo: Depositphotos.com</figcaption></figure><main class="px-4"><p data-end="314" data-start="117">The next Dutch government plans to overhaul the current public broadcasting system to create four umbrella broadcasters, replacing the current 11 separate broadcasting companies in 2027.</p><p data-end="565" data-start="316">The shake-up is necessary to cut overheads, given the need to slash spending, officials say. The outgoing administration planned to cut €160 million from the public broadcasters’ budget, but it is not yet clear if the new coalition will press ahead with the spending cuts.</p><p data-end="732" data-start="567">The three parties in talks on forming a minority coalition can count on the support of the GroenLinks-PvdA alliance, allowing consolidation plan to pass through parliament. But the left wing group has said it wants to reduce the scope of the cuts.</p><p data-end="732" data-start="567"><div class="ad-container overflow-hidden p-4 bg-light my-8 d-none d-md-block"><div class="bg-light p-lg-2 h-100 w-100 d-flex align-items-center justify-content-center position-relative" data-tagname="ROS_Inarticle"><div id="div-gpt-ad-dutchnews_ros_inarticle" style="display:block;"></div></div></div><div class="ad-container overflow-hidden p-4 bg-light my-8 d-block d-md-none"><div class="bg-light p-lg-2 h-100 w-100 d-flex align-items-center justify-content-center position-relative" data-tagname="ROS_Inarticle"><div id="div-gpt-ad-dutchnews_ros_inarticle-m" style="display:block;"></div></div></div></p><p data-end="992" data-start="734">Over the past few months, public broadcasters have been going public with lists of programmes that will be dropped because of the spending squeeze. They include the consumer affairs programme Kassa and football show Studio Voetbal, which has been a fixture for 25 years.</p><p data-end="1111" data-start="994">But the plans have irritated MPs and the public alike, with calls for a rethink on the type of programming being cut. In particular, they say, public interest programmes should not be hit.</p><p data-end="1308" data-start="1113">The Dutch public broadcasting system, NPO, is funded partly by advertising and partly by the treasury. The amount of airtime each organisation receives depends on how many members it can attract.</p><p data-end="1308" data-start="1113"><div class="ad-container overflow-hidden p-4 bg-light my-8 d-none d-md-block"><div class="bg-light p-lg-2 h-100 w-100 d-flex align-items-center justify-content-center position-relative" data-tagname="ROS_Incontent"><div id="div-gpt-ad-dutchnews_ros_incontent" style="display:block;"></div></div></div><div class="ad-container overflow-hidden p-4 bg-light my-8 d-block d-md-none"><div class="bg-light p-lg-2 h-100 w-100 d-flex align-items-center justify-content-center position-relative" data-tagname="ROS_Incontent"><div id="div-gpt-ad-dutchnews_ros_incontent-m" style="display:block;"></div></div></div></p><p data-end="1587" data-start="1310">There are currently 11 public broadcasting organisations under the NPO umbrella: AVROTROS, BNNVARA, EO, HUMAN, KRO-NCRV, MAX, ON!, PowNed, VPRO, WNL and ZWART. In addition, the news broadcaster NOS and several specialist and regional broadcasters contribute to the programming.</p><p data-end="1782" data-start="1589">Together, they provide content for three national television channels, five radio stations and several digital platforms. Each broadcaster has a particular religious, political or social focus.</p><p data-end="1905" data-is-last-node="" data-is-only-node="" data-start="1784">For example, ON!, which joined the public broadcasting system in 2021, is supported by the far-right PVV and FvD parties.</p></main><div class="ad-container overflow-hidden d-none d-md-block p-4 bg-light mt-8 mb-10 mx-lg-4"><div class="bg-light p-lg-2 h-100 w-100 d-flex align-items-center justify-content-center position-relative" data-tagname="ROS_Native"><div id="div-gpt-ad-dutchnews_ros_native" style="display:block;"></div></div></div><div class="ad-container overflow-hidden d-block d-md-none bg-light my-8"><div class="bg-light p-lg-2 h-100 w-100 d-flex align-items-center justify-content-center position-relative" data-tagname="ROS_Native"><div id="div-gpt-ad-dutchnews_ros_native-m" style="display:block;"></div></div></div><footer class="my-8 px-4"><div class="pb-8"></div> <a class="btn btn-secondary btn-sm" href="/category/art-and-culture/?list"></a> <a class="btn btn-secondary btn-sm" href="/category/media/?list"></a> <a class="btn btn-secondary btn-sm" href="/category/society/?list"></a></footer><div class="bg-green-light p-3 mx-4 mt-8 mb-12"></div></article>]]></description><guid>https://www.dutchnews.nl/?p=262754</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 09:23:52 -0000</pubDate><dc:creator><![CDATA[Robin Pascoe]]></dc:creator></item><item><title>IamExpat Fair Amsterdam is back: What’s new this year?</title><link>https://www.dutchnews.nl/2026/01/iamexpat-fair-amsterdam-is-back-whats-new-this-year/</link><description><![CDATA[<article class="post-262658 post type-post status-publish format-standard has-post-thumbnail hentry category-amsterdam category-expats"><header class="pb-4 px-4"><h5 class="text-primary"> Partner content</h5><h1 class="text-serif lh-1"> IamExpat Fair Amsterdam is back: What’s new this year?</h1> <time class="text-secondary updated me-2" datetime="2026-01-27T09:05:41+00:00"> January 27, 2026 </time></header><figure aria-describedby="caption-attachment-262661" class="px-lg-5" id="attachment_262661"> <img alt="" class="attachment-full size-full wp-post-image" decoding="async" fetchpriority="high" height="798" sizes="(max-width: 1200px) 100vw, 1200px" src="/wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/AMS-Fair-2026-Press-Photos-1.jpg" srcset="/wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/AMS-Fair-2026-Press-Photos-1.jpg 1200w, /wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/AMS-Fair-2026-Press-Photos-1-560x372.jpg 560w, /wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/AMS-Fair-2026-Press-Photos-1-360x240.jpg 360w, /wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/AMS-Fair-2026-Press-Photos-1-768x511.jpg 768w" width="1200"/><figcaption class="px-4 px-lg-0" id="caption-attachment-262661"> The Beurs van Berlage is an atmospheric setting for the fair. Photo: IamExpat Media</figcaption></figure><main class="px-4"><p data-end="437" data-start="131"><strong>Looking to make the most of your life in the Netherlands, to get your Dutch up to scratch and ask experts all those questions which have been bugging you? Help is at hand. <a href="https://amsterdam.iamexpatfair.nl/#/?affl=DNArticle">Tickets are now available</a> for the Amsterdam edition of the <span class="hover:entity-accent entity-underline inline cursor-pointer align-baseline"><span class="whitespace-normal">IamExpat Fair</span></span> at the <span class="hover:entity-accent entity-underline inline cursor-pointer align-baseline"><span class="whitespace-normal">Beurs van Berlage</span></span> in the city centre.</strong></p><p data-end="437" data-start="131">The event on March 7 is the 21st fair to be organised by the IamExpat team and, says event manager Claire <span class="im">Leunissen</span>, is set to be the best one yet. “I think the number of exhibitors will be close to 100 this year,” says Claire, who is hard at work overseeing the organisation, developing workshops and finalising the list of stand holders.</p><p data-end="917" data-start="609">“For this year we have developed a special app which will make it easier for visitors to interact, register for workshops and make the most of the day,” she says. “All of your fair tickets, including general admission and workshops, will be in one convenient location instead of attached to separate confirmation emails, and you can see instantly if there is still space at a tax workshop, for example.”</p><figure aria-describedby="caption-attachment-262659" class="wp-caption alignnone" id="attachment_262659" style="width: 560px"><noscript><img alt="" class="size-medium wp-image-262659" decoding="async" height="374" sizes="(max-width: 560px) 100vw, 560px" src="/wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/AMS-Fair-2026-Press-Photos-8-560x374.jpg" srcset="/wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/AMS-Fair-2026-Press-Photos-8-560x374.jpg 560w, /wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/AMS-Fair-2026-Press-Photos-8-360x240.jpg 360w, /wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/AMS-Fair-2026-Press-Photos-8-768x513.jpg 768w, /wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/AMS-Fair-2026-Press-Photos-8.jpg 1200w" width="560"/></noscript><img alt="" class="lazyload size-medium wp-image-262659" data-sizes="(max-width: 560px) 100vw, 560px" data-src="/wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/AMS-Fair-2026-Press-Photos-8-560x374.jpg" data-srcset="/wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/AMS-Fair-2026-Press-Photos-8-560x374.jpg 560w, /wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/AMS-Fair-2026-Press-Photos-8-360x240.jpg 360w, /wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/AMS-Fair-2026-Press-Photos-8-768x513.jpg 768w, /wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/AMS-Fair-2026-Press-Photos-8.jpg 1200w" decoding="async" height="374" src="data:image/svg+xml,%3Csvg%20xmlns=%22http://www.w3.org/2000/svg%22%20viewBox=%220%200%20560%20374%22%3E%3C/svg%3E" width="560"/><figcaption class="wp-caption-text" id="caption-attachment-262659">Sit down and relax with a coffee. Photo: IamExpat Media</figcaption></figure><p data-end="1231" data-start="919">The <a href="https://amsterdam.iamexpatfair.nl/#/?affl=DNArticle">IamExpat Fair</a> is an international one-day event designed to support the expat community in the Netherlands. Visitors can find out more about buying a house, filing their taxes and boosting their career, and this year staffing agency <span class="hover:entity-accent entity-underline inline cursor-pointer align-baseline"><span class="whitespace-normal">Undutchables</span></span> is making a welcome return to the jobs section.</p><p data-end="1556" data-start="1233">In Amsterdam, the city council’s specialised service for international residents will also be back to share more information about life in the Dutch capital. The David Lloyd gym chain is exhibiting this year for those looking to get fit, and visitors with young children can explore international education options as well.</p><p data-end="1853" data-start="1558">Legal issues are another hot topic among the international community. “People always have questions about immigration and visas, and we are very pleased to have a couple of exhibitors from specialised law firms who are hosting workshops, so people can ask their questions directly,” Claire says.</p><figure aria-describedby="caption-attachment-262660" class="wp-caption alignnone" id="attachment_262660" style="width: 560px"><noscript><img alt="" class="size-medium wp-image-262660" decoding="async" height="372" sizes="(max-width: 560px) 100vw, 560px" src="/wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/AMS-Fair-2026-Press-Photos-10-560x372.jpg" srcset="/wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/AMS-Fair-2026-Press-Photos-10-560x372.jpg 560w, /wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/AMS-Fair-2026-Press-Photos-10-360x240.jpg 360w, /wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/AMS-Fair-2026-Press-Photos-10-768x511.jpg 768w, /wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/AMS-Fair-2026-Press-Photos-10.jpg 1200w" width="560"/></noscript><img alt="" class="lazyload size-medium wp-image-262660" data-sizes="(max-width: 560px) 100vw, 560px" data-src="/wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/AMS-Fair-2026-Press-Photos-10-560x372.jpg" data-srcset="/wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/AMS-Fair-2026-Press-Photos-10-560x372.jpg 560w, /wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/AMS-Fair-2026-Press-Photos-10-360x240.jpg 360w, /wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/AMS-Fair-2026-Press-Photos-10-768x511.jpg 768w, /wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/AMS-Fair-2026-Press-Photos-10.jpg 1200w" decoding="async" height="372" src="data:image/svg+xml,%3Csvg%20xmlns=%22http://www.w3.org/2000/svg%22%20viewBox=%220%200%20560%20372%22%3E%3C/svg%3E" width="560"/><figcaption class="wp-caption-text" id="caption-attachment-262660">Find out all about buying a house. Photo: IamExpat Media</figcaption></figure><p data-end="2116" data-start="1855">Those considering learning Dutch, or struggling to make progress, will also find plenty of advice. And for visitors with problems with their landlord, or questions about tenant rights, the team from <span class="hover:entity-accent entity-underline inline cursor-pointer align-baseline"><span class="whitespace-normal">Woon!</span></span> will be on hand to help.</p><p data-end="2116" data-start="1855">“The fair really has become an established part of the international community’s calendar,” says Claire. “And we are delighted that we can do our bit in making expats feel at home.”</p><p data-end="2221" data-start="2118"><a href="https://amsterdam.iamexpatfair.nl/#/?affl=DNArticle">Free tickets to attend the fair</a> can be ordered until February 3, after which they will cost €5 each (with a special two for the price of one deal for the first week).</p><p data-end="2367" data-is-last-node="" data-is-only-node="" data-start="2223"><em>The IamExpat Fair in Amsterdam takes place at the Beurs van Berlage, a short walk from Amsterdam Central Station, on March 7 from 10 am to 5 pm.</em></p></main><div class="ad-container overflow-hidden d-none d-md-block p-4 bg-light mt-8 mb-10 mx-lg-4"><div class="bg-light p-lg-2 h-100 w-100 d-flex align-items-center justify-content-center position-relative" data-tagname="ROS_Native"><div id="div-gpt-ad-dutchnews_ros_native" style="display:block;"></div></div></div><div class="ad-container overflow-hidden d-block d-md-none bg-light my-8"><div class="bg-light p-lg-2 h-100 w-100 d-flex align-items-center justify-content-center position-relative" data-tagname="ROS_Native"><div id="div-gpt-ad-dutchnews_ros_native-m" style="display:block;"></div></div></div><footer class="my-8 px-4"><div class="pb-8"></div> <a class="btn btn-secondary btn-sm" href="/category/amsterdam/?list"></a> <a class="btn btn-secondary btn-sm" href="/category/expats/?list"></a></footer><div class="bg-green-light p-3 mx-4 mt-8 mb-12"></div></article>]]></description><guid>https://www.dutchnews.nl/?p=262658</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 09:05:41 -0000</pubDate><dc:creator><![CDATA[Robin Pascoe]]></dc:creator></item><item><title>Dutch reservists save man stuck on Scottish mountain</title><link>https://www.dutchnews.nl/2026/01/dutch-reservists-save-man-stuck-on-scottish-mountain/</link><description><![CDATA[<article class="post-262742 post type-post status-publish format-standard has-post-thumbnail hentry category-armed-forces category-defence"><header class="pb-4 px-4"><h1 class="text-serif lh-1"> Dutch reservists save man stuck on Scottish mountain</h1> <time class="text-secondary updated me-2" datetime="2026-01-27T09:02:15+00:00"> January 27, 2026 </time></header><figure aria-describedby="caption-attachment-262747" class="px-lg-5" id="attachment_262747"> <img alt="" class="attachment-full size-full wp-post-image" decoding="async" fetchpriority="high" height="1067" sizes="(max-width: 1600px) 100vw, 1600px" src="/wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/defence-ministry-rescue.jpg" srcset="/wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/defence-ministry-rescue.jpg 1600w, /wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/defence-ministry-rescue-560x373.jpg 560w, /wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/defence-ministry-rescue-1200x800.jpg 1200w, /wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/defence-ministry-rescue-360x240.jpg 360w, /wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/defence-ministry-rescue-768x512.jpg 768w, /wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/defence-ministry-rescue-1536x1024.jpg 1536w" width="1600"/><figcaption class="px-4 px-lg-0" id="caption-attachment-262747"> The rescue in progress. Photo: Defence Ministry</figcaption></figure><main class="px-4"><p>Reservists from the Dutch Marine Corps saved a man stranded near the top of Ben Nevis in Scotland on Friday while out on a mountain patrol in bad weather conditions, the Dutch defence ministry has <a href="https://www.defensie.nl/actueel/nieuws/2026/01/26/reservisten-van-de-marine-redden-man-op-ben-nevis-in-schotland">said</a>.</p><p>The group was on the 1,345 metre high mountain as part of their training when they spotted a man, vaguely visible through the mist and snow. He was unable to walk, seemed confused and did not have a compass or map.</p><p>The marines wrapped him up in a warm coat and then set about improvising a stretcher, using a water-tight sleeping bag, ropes and a mat, and dragged him down the slope.</p><div class="ad-container overflow-hidden p-4 bg-light my-8 d-none d-md-block"><div class="bg-light p-lg-2 h-100 w-100 d-flex align-items-center justify-content-center position-relative" data-tagname="ROS_Inarticle"><div id="div-gpt-ad-dutchnews_ros_inarticle" style="display:block;"></div></div></div><div class="ad-container overflow-hidden p-4 bg-light my-8 d-block d-md-none"><div class="bg-light p-lg-2 h-100 w-100 d-flex align-items-center justify-content-center position-relative" data-tagname="ROS_Inarticle"><div id="div-gpt-ad-dutchnews_ros_inarticle-m" style="display:block;"></div></div></div><p>Once below the snowline the man could walk but police were called to make sure he was ok, the ministry said.</p><p>According to section commander sergeant Onno Lankhaar, the man was lucky to be found. “If we hadn’t spotted him, he wouldn’t have made it,” he said.</p><p>The reservists are currently on a mountain training exercise in Scotland with the British Royal Reserves, which includes mountain rescues. “On Friday they were able to put what they learned into practice,” the ministry said.</p><p>Ben Nevis is Britain’s highest mountain.</p></main><div class="ad-container overflow-hidden d-none d-md-block p-4 bg-light mt-8 mb-10 mx-lg-4"><div class="bg-light p-lg-2 h-100 w-100 d-flex align-items-center justify-content-center position-relative" data-tagname="ROS_Native"><div id="div-gpt-ad-dutchnews_ros_native" style="display:block;"></div></div></div><div class="ad-container overflow-hidden d-block d-md-none bg-light my-8"><div class="bg-light p-lg-2 h-100 w-100 d-flex align-items-center justify-content-center position-relative" data-tagname="ROS_Native"><div id="div-gpt-ad-dutchnews_ros_native-m" style="display:block;"></div></div></div><footer class="my-8 px-4"><div class="pb-8"></div> <a class="btn btn-secondary btn-sm" href="/category/armed-forces/?list"></a> <a class="btn btn-secondary btn-sm" href="/category/defence/?list"></a></footer><div class="bg-green-light p-3 mx-4 mt-8 mb-12"></div></article>]]></description><guid>https://www.dutchnews.nl/?p=262742</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 09:02:15 -0000</pubDate><dc:creator><![CDATA[Hanneke Sanou]]></dc:creator></item><item><title>Dutch clubs face decisive European week as Portugal closes in</title><link>https://www.dutchnews.nl/2026/01/dutch-clubs-face-decisive-european-week-as-portugal-closes-in/</link><description><![CDATA[<article class="post-262741 post type-post status-publish format-standard has-post-thumbnail hentry category-ajax category-champions-league category-feyenoord category-football category-psv-eindhoven category-sport"><header class="pb-4 px-4"><h1 class="text-serif lh-1"> Dutch clubs face decisive European week as Portugal closes in</h1> <time class="text-secondary updated me-2" datetime="2026-01-27T08:53:16+00:00"> January 27, 2026 </time></header><figure aria-describedby="caption-attachment-233901" class="px-lg-5" id="attachment_233901"> <img alt="" class="attachment-full size-full wp-post-image" decoding="async" fetchpriority="high" height="1333" sizes="(max-width: 2000px) 100vw, 2000px" src="/wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/Depositphotos_118636018_L.jpg" srcset="/wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/Depositphotos_118636018_L.jpg 2000w, /wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/Depositphotos_118636018_L-560x373.jpg 560w, /wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/Depositphotos_118636018_L-1200x800.jpg 1200w, /wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/Depositphotos_118636018_L-360x240.jpg 360w, /wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/Depositphotos_118636018_L-768x512.jpg 768w, /wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/Depositphotos_118636018_L-1536x1024.jpg 1536w" width="2000"/><figcaption class="px-4 px-lg-0" id="caption-attachment-233901"> Photo: Depositphotos</figcaption></figure><main class="px-4"><p data-end="343" data-start="83">Five Dutch clubs play their final matches of the league phase in European competition this week and the games could prove decisive for the Netherlands’ position on the Uefa coefficient ranking.</p><p data-end="613" data-start="345">The Netherlands is in danger of losing its sixth place on the coefficient list to Portugal which will have direct consequences for the number of European places available to Dutch clubs in 2027.</p><p data-end="920" data-start="615">The Netherlands is still benefiting from an exceptionally strong coefficient season in 2021/22, when Feyenoord reached the Conference League final and Ajax won all their Champions League group matches.</p><p data-end="920" data-start="615"><div class="ad-container overflow-hidden p-4 bg-light my-8 d-none d-md-block"><div class="bg-light p-lg-2 h-100 w-100 d-flex align-items-center justify-content-center position-relative" data-tagname="ROS_Inarticle"><div id="div-gpt-ad-dutchnews_ros_inarticle" style="display:block;"></div></div></div><div class="ad-container overflow-hidden p-4 bg-light my-8 d-block d-md-none"><div class="bg-light p-lg-2 h-100 w-100 d-flex align-items-center justify-content-center position-relative" data-tagname="ROS_Inarticle"><div id="div-gpt-ad-dutchnews_ros_inarticle-m" style="display:block;"></div></div></div></p><p data-end="1207" data-start="922">However, that season is now about to drop out of the five-year calculation on which the coefficient ranking is based.</p><p data-end="1542" data-start="1209">The coefficient list determines how many clubs each country may enter into European competitions. The higher a country ranks, the more places it receives. England, Spain, Germany and Italy each have four Champions League spots. The Netherlands currently has two direct Champions League tickets and one place in the qualifying rounds.</p><p data-end="1950" data-start="1544">If the Netherlands drops to seventh, it will lose one direct Champions League spot and the total number of Dutch clubs playing European football would also fall from six to five.</p><p data-end="1950" data-start="1544">At the start of this season, data models gave the Netherlands a 79% chance of holding on to sixth place. After weak performances by Dutch teams and strong results from Portuguese clubs, that probability has now fallen to just 5.5%, <a href="https://nos.nl/artikel/2599850-coefficientenweek-van-de-waarheid-voor-nederlandse-clubs-met-portugal-hijgend-in-de-nek">broadcaster NOS reported</a>.</p><p data-end="1950" data-start="1544"><div class="ad-container overflow-hidden p-4 bg-light my-8 d-none d-md-block"><div class="bg-light p-lg-2 h-100 w-100 d-flex align-items-center justify-content-center position-relative" data-tagname="ROS_Incontent"><div id="div-gpt-ad-dutchnews_ros_incontent" style="display:block;"></div></div></div><div class="ad-container overflow-hidden p-4 bg-light my-8 d-block d-md-none"><div class="bg-light p-lg-2 h-100 w-100 d-flex align-items-center justify-content-center position-relative" data-tagname="ROS_Incontent"><div id="div-gpt-ad-dutchnews_ros_incontent-m" style="display:block;"></div></div></div></p><p data-end="2499" data-start="2187">There is, however, still a slim chance of a turnaround this week. PSV play at home against Bayern Munich in the Champions League on Wednesday. Bayern are already assured of a top-eight finish, raising hopes in Eindhoven that the German side may rest key players, improving PSV’s chances of a win and progression.</p><p data-end="2800" data-start="2501">Ajax host Olympiakos at the same time. Even with a victory, the Amsterdam side will not be guaranteed a place in the next round and will need other results to go their way. A defeat for Benfica by Real Madrid would help, as the Portuguese club is a direct competitor on the coefficient ranking.</p><h2 data-end="2800" data-start="2501">Action this week</h2><p data-end="3064" data-start="2802">Dutch clubs in the Europa League are in action on Thursday. Feyenoord travel to Real Betis, who remain firmly in contention for a top-eight finish. Go Ahead Eagles face Sporting Braga and could boost both their own prospects and the Dutch coefficient with a win.</p><p data-end="3215" data-start="3066">Even then, qualification remains unlikely. Data models give Feyenoord a 12.1% chance of reaching the next round, while Go Ahead Eagles stand at 3.8%.</p><p data-end="3394" data-is-last-node="" data-is-only-node="" data-start="3217">FC Utrecht have an away match against Celtic. Utrecht are already out of the competition but a win would still boost the coefficient.</p><p data-end="3394" data-is-last-node="" data-is-only-node="" data-start="3217">In the Conference League, AZ meet Noah of Armenia in the playoffs for a place in the knock out rounds on February 19.</p></main><div class="ad-container overflow-hidden d-none d-md-block p-4 bg-light mt-8 mb-10 mx-lg-4"><div class="bg-light p-lg-2 h-100 w-100 d-flex align-items-center justify-content-center position-relative" data-tagname="ROS_Native"><div id="div-gpt-ad-dutchnews_ros_native" style="display:block;"></div></div></div><div class="ad-container overflow-hidden d-block d-md-none bg-light my-8"><div class="bg-light p-lg-2 h-100 w-100 d-flex align-items-center justify-content-center position-relative" data-tagname="ROS_Native"><div id="div-gpt-ad-dutchnews_ros_native-m" style="display:block;"></div></div></div><footer class="my-8 px-4"><div class="pb-8"></div> <a class="btn btn-secondary btn-sm" href="/category/football/ajax/?list"></a> <a class="btn btn-secondary btn-sm" href="/category/football/champions-league/?list"></a> <a class="btn btn-secondary btn-sm" href="/category/football/feyenoord/?list"></a> <a class="btn btn-secondary btn-sm" href="/category/football/?list"></a> <a class="btn btn-secondary btn-sm" href="/category/football/psv-eindhoven/?list"></a> <a class="btn btn-secondary btn-sm" href="/category/sport/?list"></a></footer><div class="bg-green-light p-3 mx-4 mt-8 mb-12"></div></article>]]></description><guid>https://www.dutchnews.nl/?p=262741</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 08:53:16 -0000</pubDate><dc:creator><![CDATA[Robin Pascoe]]></dc:creator></item><item><title>Leave the beluga alone, says whale protection organisation</title><link>https://www.dutchnews.nl/2026/01/leave-the-beluga-alone-says-whale-protection-organisation/</link><description><![CDATA[<article class="post-262733 post type-post status-publish format-standard has-post-thumbnail hentry category-animal-welfare category-society"><header class="pb-4 px-4"><h1 class="text-serif lh-1"> Leave the beluga alone, says whale protection organisation</h1> <time class="text-secondary updated me-2" datetime="2026-01-27T08:33:32+00:00"> January 27, 2026 </time></header><figure aria-describedby="caption-attachment-262738" class="px-lg-5" id="attachment_262738"> <img alt="" class="attachment-full size-full wp-post-image" decoding="async" fetchpriority="high" height="1366" sizes="(max-width: 2048px) 100vw, 2048px" src="/wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/617930836_1232901262275860_2021364084790526927_n.jpg" srcset="/wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/617930836_1232901262275860_2021364084790526927_n.jpg 2048w, /wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/617930836_1232901262275860_2021364084790526927_n-560x374.jpg 560w, /wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/617930836_1232901262275860_2021364084790526927_n-1200x800.jpg 1200w, /wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/617930836_1232901262275860_2021364084790526927_n-360x240.jpg 360w, /wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/617930836_1232901262275860_2021364084790526927_n-768x512.jpg 768w, /wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/617930836_1232901262275860_2021364084790526927_n-1536x1025.jpg 1536w" width="2048"/><figcaption class="px-4 px-lg-0" id="caption-attachment-262738"> A drone hovering over the beluga. Photo: Jeroen Hoekendijk, SOS Dolfijn</figcaption></figure><main class="px-4"><p>Animal protection organisation SOS Dolfijn has urged whale spotters to stop bothering the beluga which has been swimming off the coast of the Netherlands over the past few days.</p><p>People who are taking boats out or sending up drones are distressing the animal, and should back off, the organisation said. Instead, enthusiasts should “enjoy this unique moment from the beach”, according to spokesman Jeroen Hoekendijk.</p><p>The beluga put in a rare appearance some 10 days ago and has been around since then. It was last spotted between Egmond and Castricum.</p><div class="ad-container overflow-hidden p-4 bg-light my-8 d-none d-md-block"><div class="bg-light p-lg-2 h-100 w-100 d-flex align-items-center justify-content-center position-relative" data-tagname="ROS_Inarticle"><div id="div-gpt-ad-dutchnews_ros_inarticle" style="display:block;"></div></div></div><div class="ad-container overflow-hidden p-4 bg-light my-8 d-block d-md-none"><div class="bg-light p-lg-2 h-100 w-100 d-flex align-items-center justify-content-center position-relative" data-tagname="ROS_Inarticle"><div id="div-gpt-ad-dutchnews_ros_inarticle-m" style="display:block;"></div></div></div><p>SOS Dolfijn denied that their own publicity around the animal is boosting nuisance filming. “We know that this sort of thing gets out anyway and we prefer to inform people how to observe the animal in the right way,” Hoekendijk told local media.</p><p>The last time a white whale visited Dutch shores was in 1984. The waters of the Arctic and sub-Arctic around Russia, Canada, Alaska and Greenland form its usual habitat.</p></main><div class="ad-container overflow-hidden d-none d-md-block p-4 bg-light mt-8 mb-10 mx-lg-4"><div class="bg-light p-lg-2 h-100 w-100 d-flex align-items-center justify-content-center position-relative" data-tagname="ROS_Native"><div id="div-gpt-ad-dutchnews_ros_native" style="display:block;"></div></div></div><div class="ad-container overflow-hidden d-block d-md-none bg-light my-8"><div class="bg-light p-lg-2 h-100 w-100 d-flex align-items-center justify-content-center position-relative" data-tagname="ROS_Native"><div id="div-gpt-ad-dutchnews_ros_native-m" style="display:block;"></div></div></div><footer class="my-8 px-4"><div class="pb-8"></div> <a class="btn btn-secondary btn-sm" href="/category/animal-welfare/?list"></a> <a class="btn btn-secondary btn-sm" href="/category/society/?list"></a></footer><div class="bg-green-light p-3 mx-4 mt-8 mb-12"></div></article>]]></description><guid>https://www.dutchnews.nl/?p=262733</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 08:33:32 -0000</pubDate><dc:creator><![CDATA[Hanneke Sanou]]></dc:creator></item><item><title>Lidl NL, Albert Heijn and Jumbo top green supermarket ranking</title><link>https://www.dutchnews.nl/2026/01/lidl-nl-albert-heijn-and-jumbo-top-green-supermarket-ranking/</link><description><![CDATA[<article class="post-262731 post type-post status-publish format-standard has-post-thumbnail hentry category-business category-environment category-food-industry category-food-prices category-supermarkets"><header class="pb-4 px-4"><h1 class="text-serif lh-1"> Lidl NL, Albert Heijn and Jumbo top green supermarket ranking</h1> <time class="text-secondary updated me-2" datetime="2026-01-27T08:01:57+00:00"> January 27, 2026 </time></header><figure aria-describedby="caption-attachment-184628" class="px-lg-5" id="attachment_184628"> <img alt="" class="attachment-full size-full wp-post-image" decoding="async" fetchpriority="high" height="593" sizes="(max-width: 999px) 100vw, 999px" src="/wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Depositphotos_159012478_S.jpg" srcset="/wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Depositphotos_159012478_S.jpg 999w, /wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Depositphotos_159012478_S-560x332.jpg 560w, /wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Depositphotos_159012478_S-768x456.jpg 768w, /wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Depositphotos_159012478_S-640x380.jpg 640w, /wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Depositphotos_159012478_S-92x55.jpg 92w, /wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Depositphotos_159012478_S-130x77.jpg 130w" width="999"/><figcaption class="px-4 px-lg-0" id="caption-attachment-184628"> Photo: Depositphotos.com</figcaption></figure><main class="px-4"><p data-end="291" data-start="133">Lidl Nederland is the greenest European supermarket, followed by Lidl Poland, Albert Heijn and Jumbo, according to supermarket sector think-tank Questionmark.</p><p data-end="637" data-start="293">The organisation studied 27 large supermarket chains in eight European countries, looking at their sustainability strategies and their contribution to the shift from animal to vegetable protein.</p><p data-end="637" data-start="293">Consumers, the agency said, buy 70% of their food in supermarkets, and their role in the food chain is an important factor in solving environmental issues.</p><p data-end="637" data-start="293"><div class="ad-container overflow-hidden p-4 bg-light my-8 d-none d-md-block"><div class="bg-light p-lg-2 h-100 w-100 d-flex align-items-center justify-content-center position-relative" data-tagname="ROS_Inarticle"><div id="div-gpt-ad-dutchnews_ros_inarticle" style="display:block;"></div></div></div><div class="ad-container overflow-hidden p-4 bg-light my-8 d-block d-md-none"><div class="bg-light p-lg-2 h-100 w-100 d-flex align-items-center justify-content-center position-relative" data-tagname="ROS_Inarticle"><div id="div-gpt-ad-dutchnews_ros_inarticle-m" style="display:block;"></div></div></div></p><p data-end="861" data-start="639">Just seven of the supermarket groups, including Lidl Nederland and AH, have a detailed plan to help them meet the Paris climate change targets by 2050, although none of the plans are currently on target, Questionmark said.</p><p data-end="1107" data-start="863">The three Dutch supermarkets also plan to ensure that vegetable protein accounts for 60% of sales by 2030, but are not on target to do so either. In fact, the figures show the percentage of vegetable protein sold via AH supermarkets has fallen to 44%.</p><p data-end="1482" data-is-last-node="" data-is-only-node="" data-start="1109">“Dutch supermarkets have ambitious targets which fit an eating pattern that dovetails with ecological limits, and they are an example for other European supermarkets,” said WWF sustainable food advisor Corné van Dooren.</p><p data-end="1482" data-is-last-node="" data-is-only-node="" data-start="1109">“At the same time, they are going to have to start making their plans come true, and more needs to be done to stimulate people to eat vegetable protein.”</p></main><div class="ad-container overflow-hidden d-none d-md-block p-4 bg-light mt-8 mb-10 mx-lg-4"><div class="bg-light p-lg-2 h-100 w-100 d-flex align-items-center justify-content-center position-relative" data-tagname="ROS_Native"><div id="div-gpt-ad-dutchnews_ros_native" style="display:block;"></div></div></div><div class="ad-container overflow-hidden d-block d-md-none bg-light my-8"><div class="bg-light p-lg-2 h-100 w-100 d-flex align-items-center justify-content-center position-relative" data-tagname="ROS_Native"><div id="div-gpt-ad-dutchnews_ros_native-m" style="display:block;"></div></div></div><footer class="my-8 px-4"><div class="pb-8"></div> <a class="btn btn-secondary btn-sm" href="/category/business/?list"></a> <a class="btn btn-secondary btn-sm" href="/category/environment/?list"></a> <a class="btn btn-secondary btn-sm" href="/category/food-industry/?list"></a> <a class="btn btn-secondary btn-sm" href="/category/food-prices/?list"></a> <a class="btn btn-secondary btn-sm" href="/category/supermarkets/?list"></a></footer><div class="bg-green-light p-3 mx-4 mt-8 mb-12"></div></article>]]></description><guid>https://www.dutchnews.nl/?p=262731</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 08:01:57 -0000</pubDate><dc:creator><![CDATA[Robin Pascoe]]></dc:creator></item><item><title>US ambassador says Trump’s allies comments “not directed at NL”</title><link>https://www.dutchnews.nl/2026/01/us-ambassador-says-trumps-allies-comments-not-directed-at-nl/</link><description><![CDATA[<article class="post-262723 post type-post status-publish format-standard has-post-thumbnail hentry category-afghanistan category-armed-forces category-foreign-affairs category-us"><header class="pb-4 px-4"><h1 class="text-serif lh-1"> US ambassador says Trump’s allies comments “not directed at NL”</h1> <time class="text-secondary updated me-2" datetime="2026-01-26T16:59:59+00:00"> January 26, 2026 </time></header><figure aria-describedby="caption-attachment-250036" class="px-lg-5" id="attachment_250036"> <img alt="" class="attachment-full size-full wp-post-image" decoding="async" fetchpriority="high" height="533" sizes="(max-width: 799px) 100vw, 799px" src="/wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/41008845962_29a3bca463_c.jpg" srcset="/wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/41008845962_29a3bca463_c.jpg 799w, /wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/41008845962_29a3bca463_c-560x374.jpg 560w, /wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/41008845962_29a3bca463_c-360x240.jpg 360w, /wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/41008845962_29a3bca463_c-768x512.jpg 768w" width="799"/><figcaption class="px-4 px-lg-0" id="caption-attachment-250036"> The US embassy near The Hague. Photo: US embassy via Flickr</figcaption></figure><main class="px-4"><p data-end="377" data-start="153">The US ambassador to the Netherlands has issued a <a href="https://x.com/usambnl/status/2015709598179557494">statement on social media</a> in which he says he sees “no indication” that president Donald Trump’s comments about Nato allies in Afghanistan were directed at the Netherlands.</p><p data-end="554" data-start="379">Ambassador Joe Popolo was <a href="https://www.dutchnews.nl/2026/01/dutch-condemn-trumps-comments-about-nato-troops-in-afghanistan/">responding to angry comments</a> from politicians, Dutch army veterans and relatives of soldiers killed in action after Trump had downplayed the role of Nato troops.</p><p data-end="872" data-start="556">During his visit to the World Economic Forum last week, Trump said Nato troops had stayed “a bit in the background” and away from the front lines during the Afghanistan mission. He also questioned whether Nato allies would “be there” if the United States “ever needed them”, comments he later repeated to Fox News.</p><p data-end="872" data-start="556"><div class="ad-container overflow-hidden p-4 bg-light my-8 d-none d-md-block"><div class="bg-light p-lg-2 h-100 w-100 d-flex align-items-center justify-content-center position-relative" data-tagname="ROS_Inarticle"><div id="div-gpt-ad-dutchnews_ros_inarticle" style="display:block;"></div></div></div><div class="ad-container overflow-hidden p-4 bg-light my-8 d-block d-md-none"><div class="bg-light p-lg-2 h-100 w-100 d-flex align-items-center justify-content-center position-relative" data-tagname="ROS_Inarticle"><div id="div-gpt-ad-dutchnews_ros_inarticle-m" style="display:block;"></div></div></div></p><p data-end="872" data-start="556">Between 2002 and 2021, the Netherlands deployed more than 30,000 service personnel to Afghanistan. Twenty-five Dutch soldiers were killed, several during combat operations. In total, 51 countries took part in the ISAF mission.</p><p data-end="1446" data-start="1145">Popolo said on Monday that the “United States recognises and honours the Dutch heroes who gave their lives fighting shoulder to shoulder with American service members in Afghanistan, following the United States’ 2001 invocation of Article 5 in response to the September 11 attacks.”</p><p data-end="1641" data-start="1448">The United States, he went on, “values the Netherlands’ steadfast commitment to Nato and its dedication to defending democracy and individual freedom as part of the coalition of the willing.”</p><p data-end="1641" data-start="1448"><div class="ad-container overflow-hidden p-4 bg-light my-8 d-none d-md-block"><div class="bg-light p-lg-2 h-100 w-100 d-flex align-items-center justify-content-center position-relative" data-tagname="ROS_Incontent"><div id="div-gpt-ad-dutchnews_ros_incontent" style="display:block;"></div></div></div><div class="ad-container overflow-hidden p-4 bg-light my-8 d-block d-md-none"><div class="bg-light p-lg-2 h-100 w-100 d-flex align-items-center justify-content-center position-relative" data-tagname="ROS_Incontent"><div id="div-gpt-ad-dutchnews_ros_incontent-m" style="display:block;"></div></div></div></p><p data-end="1887" data-start="1643">Hundreds of people commented on the post, with many pointing out that Trump directed his comments at “Nato allies” in general.</p><p data-end="1887" data-start="1643">“<span class="css-1jxf684 r-bcqeeo r-1ttztb7 r-qvutc0 r-poiln3">With all due respect: Trump only bothered to walk back his statement for the UK, not for the Netherlands or other allies,” said Dutch army veteran Roy Grinwis.  “Maybe he should learn to think before he speaks, instead of leaving diplomats to clean up the mess afterwards.”</span></p><p data-end="1887" data-start="1643">Dutch foreign affairs minister David van Weel earlier described Trump’s comments as “disrespectful and untrue,” while former Dutch army major Henry Beukers told <a href="https://nos.nl/artikel/2599507-veteranen-verbijsterd-over-leugens-van-trump-over-afghanistan-missie">broadcaster NOS</a> the claim was deeply hurtful. “We fought shoulder to shoulder with the Americans on the front line,” he said.</p><p data-end="2016" data-is-last-node="" data-is-only-node="" data-start="1889">Popolo, a businessman, was nominated by former president Donald Trump in early January 2025 and <a href="https://www.dutchnews.nl/2025/10/us-senate-confirms-joe-popolo-as-new-ambassador-to-nl/">confirmed in October</a> last year.</p></main><div class="ad-container overflow-hidden d-none d-md-block p-4 bg-light mt-8 mb-10 mx-lg-4"><div class="bg-light p-lg-2 h-100 w-100 d-flex align-items-center justify-content-center position-relative" data-tagname="ROS_Native"><div id="div-gpt-ad-dutchnews_ros_native" style="display:block;"></div></div></div><div class="ad-container overflow-hidden d-block d-md-none bg-light my-8"><div class="bg-light p-lg-2 h-100 w-100 d-flex align-items-center justify-content-center position-relative" data-tagname="ROS_Native"><div id="div-gpt-ad-dutchnews_ros_native-m" style="display:block;"></div></div></div><footer class="my-8 px-4"><div class="pb-8"></div> <a class="btn btn-secondary btn-sm" href="/category/afghanistan/?list"></a> <a class="btn btn-secondary btn-sm" href="/category/armed-forces/?list"></a> <a class="btn btn-secondary btn-sm" href="/category/foreign-affairs/?list"></a> <a class="btn btn-secondary btn-sm" href="/category/us/?list"></a></footer><div class="bg-green-light p-3 mx-4 mt-8 mb-12"></div></article>]]></description><guid>https://www.dutchnews.nl/?p=262723</guid><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 16:59:59 -0000</pubDate><dc:creator><![CDATA[Robin Pascoe]]></dc:creator></item><item><title>Have your say about local council services – and vote if you can</title><link>https://www.dutchnews.nl/2026/01/have-your-say-about-local-council-services-and-vote-if-you-can/</link><description><![CDATA[<article class="post-262720 post type-post status-publish format-standard has-post-thumbnail hentry category-election category-local-government"><header class="pb-4 px-4"><h1 class="text-serif lh-1"> Have your say about local council services – and vote if you can</h1> <time class="text-secondary updated me-2" datetime="2026-01-26T15:29:51+00:00"> January 26, 2026 </time></header><figure aria-describedby="caption-attachment-258868" class="px-lg-5" id="attachment_258868"> <img alt="" class="attachment-full size-full wp-post-image" decoding="async" fetchpriority="high" height="1461" sizes="(max-width: 1948px) 100vw, 1948px" src="/wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/IMG_0498.jpg" srcset="/wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/IMG_0498.jpg 1948w, /wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/IMG_0498-560x420.jpg 560w, /wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/IMG_0498-1200x900.jpg 1200w, /wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/IMG_0498-768x576.jpg 768w, /wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/IMG_0498-1536x1152.jpg 1536w" width="1948"/><figcaption class="px-4 px-lg-0" id="caption-attachment-258868"> Photo: Dutch News</figcaption></figure><main class="px-4"><p>On March 18, the Netherlands will hold new elections – this time to elect members of the country’s 342 local councils. Unlike in the national elections, people from EU countries will be able to vote, as will non-EU nationals who have lived in the Netherlands for five years.</p><p>Dutch News will be reporting on the campaigns, the big issues and on efforts to involve the international community in the vote. To kick off, please take part in this short survey.</p><p><iframe frameborder="0" height="5159" marginheight="0" marginwidth="0" src="https://docs.google.com/forms/d/e/1FAIpQLSd8WkEgCWT3qrzwJgFlzwWVZVGG_vCyCh5xo2BnL_d6milfLg/viewform?embedded=true" width="600">Loading…</iframe></p></main><div class="ad-container overflow-hidden d-none d-md-block p-4 bg-light mt-8 mb-10 mx-lg-4"><div class="bg-light p-lg-2 h-100 w-100 d-flex align-items-center justify-content-center position-relative" data-tagname="ROS_Native"><div id="div-gpt-ad-dutchnews_ros_native" style="display:block;"></div></div></div><div class="ad-container overflow-hidden d-block d-md-none bg-light my-8"><div class="bg-light p-lg-2 h-100 w-100 d-flex align-items-center justify-content-center position-relative" data-tagname="ROS_Native"><div id="div-gpt-ad-dutchnews_ros_native-m" style="display:block;"></div></div></div><footer class="my-8 px-4"><div class="pb-8"></div> <a class="btn btn-secondary btn-sm" href="/category/election/?list"></a> <a class="btn btn-secondary btn-sm" href="/category/local-government/?list"></a></footer><div class="bg-green-light p-3 mx-4 mt-8 mb-12"></div></article>]]></description><guid>https://www.dutchnews.nl/?p=262720</guid><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 15:29:51 -0000</pubDate><dc:creator><![CDATA[Robin Pascoe]]></dc:creator></item><item><title>Dutch economy is becoming less competitive, watchdog warns</title><link>https://www.dutchnews.nl/2026/01/dutch-economy-is-becoming-less-competitive-watchdog-warns/</link><description><![CDATA[<article class="post-262716 post type-post status-publish format-standard has-post-thumbnail hentry category-business category-competition category-economy"><header class="pb-4 px-4"><h1 class="text-serif lh-1"> Dutch economy is becoming less competitive, watchdog warns</h1> <time class="text-secondary updated me-2" datetime="2026-01-26T14:18:36+00:00"> January 26, 2026 </time></header><figure aria-describedby="caption-attachment-261271" class="px-lg-5" id="attachment_261271"> <img alt="" class="attachment-full size-full wp-post-image" decoding="async" fetchpriority="high" height="667" sizes="(max-width: 1000px) 100vw, 1000px" src="/wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2025/12/Depositphotos_118554648_S.jpg" srcset="/wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2025/12/Depositphotos_118554648_S.jpg 1000w, /wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2025/12/Depositphotos_118554648_S-560x374.jpg 560w, /wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2025/12/Depositphotos_118554648_S-360x240.jpg 360w, /wpcms/wp-content/uploads/2025/12/Depositphotos_118554648_S-768x512.jpg 768w" width="1000"/><figcaption class="px-4 px-lg-0" id="caption-attachment-261271"> Photo: Depositphotos.com</figcaption></figure><main class="px-4"><div class="relative basis-auto flex-col -mb-(--composer-overlap-px) [--composer-overlap-px:28px] grow flex"><div class="flex flex-col text-sm pb-25"><article class="text-token-text-primary w-full focus:outline-none [--shadow-height:45px] has-data-writing-block:pointer-events-none has-data-writing-block:-mt-(--shadow-height) has-data-writing-block:pt-(--shadow-height) [&amp;:has([data-writing-block])&gt;*]:pointer-events-auto scroll-mt-[calc(var(--header-height)+min(200px,max(70px,20svh)))]" data-scroll-anchor="true" data-testid="conversation-turn-8" data-turn="assistant" data-turn-id="request-WEB:822f0561-28e1-43a8-9fe8-896a387e8beb-3" dir="auto" tabindex="-1"><div class="text-base my-auto mx-auto pb-10 [--thread-content-margin:--spacing(4)] @w-sm/main:[--thread-content-margin:--spacing(6)] @w-lg/main:[--thread-content-margin:--spacing(16)] px-(--thread-content-margin)"><div class="[--thread-content-max-width:40rem] @w-lg/main:[--thread-content-max-width:48rem] mx-auto max-w-(--thread-content-max-width) flex-1 group/turn-messages focus-visible:outline-hidden relative flex w-full min-w-0 flex-col agent-turn" tabindex="-1"><div class="flex max-w-full flex-col grow"><div class="min-h-8 text-message relative flex w-full flex-col items-end gap-2 text-start break-words whitespace-normal [.text-message+&amp;]:mt-1" data-message-author-role="assistant" data-message-id="8d91d388-2946-4c65-bc23-99a8ce5ae2fc" data-message-model-slug="gpt-5-2" dir="auto"><div class="flex w-full flex-col gap-1 empty:hidden first:pt-[1px]"><div class="markdown prose dark:prose-invert w-full wrap-break-word light markdown-new-styling"><p data-end="400" data-start="227">The Dutch economy has become less competitive over the past decade, raising questions about innovation and the country’s economic resilience, competition <a href="https://www.acm.nl/nl/publicaties/acm-concurrentie-draagt-bij-aan-innovatieve-en-weerbare-samenleving">watchdog ACM warned</a> on Monday.</p><p data-end="786" data-start="402">Several indicators point to a decline in competition between 2011 and 2023, and weaker competition threatens not only prices and quality but also broader public interests, including innovation, the agency said.</p><p data-end="1108" data-start="788">Markets with multiple suppliers, the ACM said, are better able to absorb disruption when one player drops out while a reduction in competition makes the economy more vulnerable. At the same time, the watchdog stressed that competition is not an end in itself and must always be weighed against other public interests.</p><p data-end="1108" data-start="788"><div class="ad-container overflow-hidden p-4 bg-light my-8 d-none d-md-block"><div class="bg-light p-lg-2 h-100 w-100 d-flex align-items-center justify-content-center position-relative" data-tagname="ROS_Inarticle"><div id="div-gpt-ad-dutchnews_ros_inarticle" style="display:block;"></div></div></div><div class="ad-container overflow-hidden p-4 bg-light my-8 d-block d-md-none"><div class="bg-light p-lg-2 h-100 w-100 d-flex align-items-center justify-content-center position-relative" data-tagname="ROS_Inarticle"><div id="div-gpt-ad-dutchnews_ros_inarticle-m" style="display:block;"></div></div></div></p><p data-end="1784" data-start="1409">“What matters is effective competition that delivers well-functioning markets for people and businesses, now and in the future,” ACM chairman <span class="hover:entity-accent entity-underline inline cursor-pointer align-baseline"><span class="whitespace-normal">Martijn Snoep</span></span> said.</p><p data-end="1784" data-start="1409">In particular the ACM warned that large companies are increasingly buying up potential challengers to eliminate future competition in innovative sectors such as digital services and pharmaceuticals.</p><p data-end="1784" data-start="1409">Such “killer acquisitions” risk stifling innovation before it reaches the market, Snoep told the Financieele Dagblad in an interview.</p><p data-end="1784" data-start="1409"><div class="ad-container overflow-hidden p-4 bg-light my-8 d-none d-md-block"><div class="bg-light p-lg-2 h-100 w-100 d-flex align-items-center justify-content-center position-relative" data-tagname="ROS_Incontent"><div id="div-gpt-ad-dutchnews_ros_incontent" style="display:block;"></div></div></div><div class="ad-container overflow-hidden p-4 bg-light my-8 d-block d-md-none"><div class="bg-light p-lg-2 h-100 w-100 d-flex align-items-center justify-content-center position-relative" data-tagname="ROS_Incontent"><div id="div-gpt-ad-dutchnews_ros_incontent-m" style="display:block;"></div></div></div></p><p data-end="2715" data-start="2385">The watchdog is also investigating the veterinary sector, where private equity-backed takeovers created a number of dominate players. The ACM has raised similar concerns about consolidation driven by private equity in areas such as childcare and accountancy for small and medium-sized businesses.</p><p data-end="3032" data-start="2717">To counter these trends, the ACM suggests a mix of measures. These include making it easier for innovative newcomers to compete with large companies and assessing small acquisitions by major firms when they risk harming competition.</p><p data-end="3362" data-start="3034">The watchdog also rejected calls to relax merger controls to allow the creation of so-called European champions, warning that looser oversight would ultimately harm productivity and competition.</p><p data-end="3362" data-start="3034">Instead, it said barriers on the European internal market should be reduced to allow companies to grow without weakening competition.</p></div></div></div></div></div></div></article></div></div></main><div class="ad-container overflow-hidden d-none d-md-block p-4 bg-light mt-8 mb-10 mx-lg-4"><div class="bg-light p-lg-2 h-100 w-100 d-flex align-items-center justify-content-center position-relative" data-tagname="ROS_Native"><div id="div-gpt-ad-dutchnews_ros_native" style="display:block;"></div></div></div><div class="ad-container overflow-hidden d-block d-md-none bg-light my-8"><div class="bg-light p-lg-2 h-100 w-100 d-flex align-items-center justify-content-center position-relative" data-tagname="ROS_Native"><div id="div-gpt-ad-dutchnews_ros_native-m" style="display:block;"></div></div></div><footer class="my-8 px-4"><div class="pb-8"></div> <a class="btn btn-secondary btn-sm" href="/category/business/?list"></a> <a class="btn btn-secondary btn-sm" href="/category/competition/?list"></a> <a class="btn btn-secondary btn-sm" href="/category/economy/?list"></a></footer><div class="bg-green-light p-3 mx-4 mt-8 mb-12"></div></article>]]></description><guid>https://www.dutchnews.nl/?p=262716</guid><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 14:18:36 -0000</pubDate><dc:creator><![CDATA[Robin Pascoe]]></dc:creator></item></channel></rss>